Preface to the First Edition

This book is written for engineers to explain some of the basic principles and practices involved in insurance for civil engineering contracts.

It concentrates on four main areas of insurance, namely the insurance of the contract works during construction, public liability, employers’ liability and professional indemnity insurance.

Most civil engineering contracts follow a similar pattern. They contain clauses that make the contractor responsible for injury or damage in certain circumstances and require him to insure against that injury or damage. Thus there will be clauses stating that the contractor is responsible for loss or damage to the contracts works in certain circumstances and must arrange insurance against that loss or damage. There will be an indemnity clause by which the contractor indemnifies the employer against claims for injury to people or damage to their property. This will be followed by an insurance clause requiring the contractor to take out employers’ liability and public liability insurance. Although the words of these clauses differ from contract to contract, the general principles remain the same. In writing this book, therefore, I have taken the ICE Conditions of Contract (5th Edition (June 1983, revised January 1979)) as a guide. In connection with sub-contractors’ responsibilities, I have taken the Federation of Civil Engineering Contractors Form of SubContract (Revised September 1984) as a guide.

Insurance is complicated and construction insurance more than most. Very often the problems are ones of definition. When it comes to interpreting the meaning of engineering contracts or insurance policies. The English language is not always sufficiently precise, and arguments as to the interpretation of words or phrases are bound to arise, particularly where very large sums of money are at stake. Those engaged in the insurance industry would say that the fault is not all of their own making since they have to respond to words and clauses in construction contracts which very often themselves lack precision. Moreover, such clauses have often been drafted without reference to the insurance industry, a common problem with many standard forms of contract. Fortunately, this situation is being remedied, although slowly. No wonder the engineer regards insurance with some feeling of trepidation.

Constraint

A constraint on this book was the necessity to keep to a maximum of 30 000 words. It is not easy to cover such a wide area in full, given such a brief. Consequently, I have concerned myself in the main with basic principles and practice and have tried to avoid undue technicality in both legal and insurance matters. Nor have I been able to deal with contracts performed outside the United Kingdom, although in the main these do not depart to any great extent from practice in the UK.

Project insurance

I have also approached the book on the basis that, as it is the contractor who in the main carries the responsibilities, it is he who arranges the insurances. There is an alternative way by which the employer arranges the insurances while still leaving the contractor with his contractual responsibilities and liabilities. Often what is known as project insurance is arranged, that is to say, the employer will arrange insurance in the joint names of himself and all contractors. There are many advantages in such an arrangement, particularly for large projects with many contractors involved, but space does not permit any detailed consideration of this type of insurance.

Insurance departments

The insurance market is divided into departments. This is because some insurers or underwriters prefer to specialise in certain risks and have no knowledge of others. Thus insurers specialising in public liability insurance may not underwrite insurance of the contract works, and insurers specialising in insurance of the contract works may not underwrite professional indemnity risks. This leads unfortunately to the result that it is often necessary to effect several insurances to cover one contract, with the possible danger of gaps appearing in the overall protection. It also explains why it is not possible to have one policy covering ‘everything’, a question often asked. Trying to obtain complete overall protection is like trying to fit the pieces of a jigsaw together, and since all policies contain limitations or exclusions of some kind the fit is often imperfect.

I have included two chapters on professional indemnity and professional indemnity insurance because of the growing interest in this subject. It is a matter of concern to most professional people, and particularly to those employed in the construction industry, that claims for breach of professional duty are on the increase and are becoming more expensive to handle and settle. That is why there has been such a sharp increase in professional indemnity premiums and why some sections of the insurance market, having sustained large losses, have discontinued underwriting this class of insurance.

Specimen policies

Some specimen insurance policies are included in the Appendices. These have to be treated with care, since they are meant to be no more than typical insurance policies which will be met in practice. There is no such thing in the insurance world as a standard contractor’s policy. Each insurer or underwriter will use his own policies and they will differ. In practice they are often altered to suit the particular requirements of the insured or his professional advisers. Often there may be an element of packaging by which several risks are included in one policy.

Importance of insurance

Insurance plays an important role in all construction projects and many of the things that go wrong are eventually paid for by insurance. Lack of insurance or inadequate insurance can often cause extensive delays and in some cases liquidation of the contractor. It is, therefore, important that the insurance industry be consulted at an early stage for advice and assistance and certainly before the contract conditions are finally drafted. Those insurers, brokers and consultants who specialise in construction insurance have much to offer in the areas of risk identification, analysis and insurance.

Many of the problems that have arisen in construction projects could have been avoided if professional insurance advice had been taken in the early stages. The insurance industry also has much to offer in the field of risk management. It would be wrong to regard the insurance industry as merely the providers of insurance protection — their role is much wider than that.

For more knowledge of the subject, and particularly a more detailed analysis of what insurance policies cover, the reader is referred to the books mentioned in Appendix 7.

The drafts of the book were read by F.N. Eaglestone, P.J. McBrien and J. Powell. I should like to express my thanks and appreciation to all of them for the helpful comments they made and to my secretary Mrs A. Meredith for typing the drafts and dealing so efficiently with my notes and tapes.

Peter Madge

April 1986

Preface to the Second Edition

The first edition of this book, Civil engineering insurance and bonding, was published in 1987. It used the insurance clauses of the then current ICE Conditions of Contract for Works of Civil Engineering Construction, 5th Edition, as a basis for describing various aspects of civil engineering insurance. Since then the ICE 5th Edition has been superseded by the ICE 6th Edition and several new ICE conditions of contract (as well as revisions to them) have also been issued. It was felt by the Editorial Panel of the ICE Engineering Management Series of books (of which this book was the first) that the time had come for an update.

The second edition follows the same format as the first edition but now covers, in particular, the following conditions of contract:

ICE Works of Civil Engineering Construction, 6th Edition (1991)
ICE Design and Construct (1992)
ICE Minor Works, 2nd Edition (1995)
ICE NEC Engineering and Construction Contract, 2nd Edition (1995)

Much use has been made of Peter Madge’s original text and all he said in his Preface to the First Edition still holds good. Besides the obvious changes necessitated by the use of clauses from the above conditions of contract instead of ICE 5th Edition, the opportunity has been taken to update the text where considered appropriate. This includes a complete rewrite of the chapter dealing with the significance of insurance in risk management.

We are greatly indebted to the groundwork so expertly laid by Peter Madge in the text of the original book and to the advice and encouragement he has provided following his review of our initial draft.

Leslie Edwards

Geoffrey Lord

London, February 1996

1
Insurance

Contractors’ All Risks insurance

The insurance of civil engineering works and of liabilities arising during and in consequence of the carrying out of the works is usually by a Contractors’ All Risks (‘CAR’) policy. Such a policy will be a combination of the first, second and, sometimes, the third of the following elements:

Material Damage insurance, which is insurance of the works which are being constructed, including materials for incorporation into the works. It is also called ‘Contract Works’ insurance.

Public Liability insurance, which is insurance of the liability of the Contractor for personal injury, damage to property and other torts.
Employer’s Liability insurance, which is insurance of the Contractor’s liability for injury to the Contractor’s employees.

Public and Employer’s Liability insurances are called ‘liability policies’ because they cover the insured’s liability for personal injury and damage to property, not the persons or property in question.

Where a project of significant size is involved there will usually be a project policy which will insure the Employer, Contractor and Sub-Contractors involved in the project. A project policy will usually be for the duration of the project and may extend cover into any maintenance period. Contractors normally, however, have an annual policy (alternatively called a floater policy) which provides insurance cover under one policy for most of their usual or smaller projects. The general provisions found in both project and annual CAR policies are similar. Project policies may, however, contain special provisions tailored for a particular project. Contract Works, Public Liability and Employer’s Liability policies will each be discussed in more detail later in this text.

The insurance market

The United Kingdom insurance market consists of insurance companies and of underwriting syndicates at Lloyd’s, who underwrite the risks; insurance brokers acting for the insured who place business with the insurers; and loss adjusters appointed on behalf of the insurers to investigate and negotiate the settlement of claims.

There are hundreds of insurers both in the United Kingdom and outside, in addition to many Lloyd’s underwriters, competing for insurance business. They do not compete only on price. The scope of the cover they offer, the terms and conditions to which it is subject, the service they are prepared to give (particularly in the handling of claims) and their reputation (for instance for fair and prompt settlement of claims) also come into play.

Construction insurers

While many insurers have a limited knowledge of the civil engineering and construction industry, there are some who specialise in construction and engineering insurance. For example, the insurers in the London Market willing to underwrite civil engineering and construction insurance have a significant degree of expertise in the insuring of civil engineering and construction risks. In some cases the underwriters (the people who consider the risk proposals and negotiate and agree the terms of the policy) are engineers or have engineering expertise available in-house. In other cases they will have a working knowledge of how a construction project is undertaken. It is now common for a CAR policy for a specific project or for contractor’s larger annual policies to be underwritten by several co-insurers from the CAR market.

Insurance brokers

The insurance broker is the agent for the insured and acts as the insured’s professional adviser in the nature and placing of the insurance required, whether it is for the project or for the contractor. As with insurers, one finds brokers who specialise in civil engineering insurance. There expertise enables them not only to indentify insurers most likely to accept the risk but to negotiate particular terms of the insurance contract to suit a client’s needs. Some of the larger contractors have subsidiary companies who act as brokers and deal with insurance matters relating to their contractor parent company.

Loss adjusters

Loss adjusters are appointed by insurers to investigate, negotiate and settle claims under the terms of the insurance policy. The larger firms have engineers and surveyors on their staff. Loss adjusters should not be confused with loss assessors who are engaged by, and act solely for, an insured in the preparation, presentation and negotiation of claims in order to obtain the best settlement for their client.

Extent of financial risk

In many civil engineering contracts the value of the contract works at risk from loss or damage is high. Moreover, claims for third party common law damages from people who have sustained injury or damage to their property as a result of construction activities are on the increase. Such risks are invariably covered by insurance. Payment of very large amounts of money by insurers may often depend upont he interpretation given to a word or phrase in a policy, or the information given by the insured when proposing the insurance or completing a proposal form.

Unfortunately many organisations have a casual approach to insurance. It has a low order of priority. As a result insufficient thought is often given to the matter by the insured, so that the information given to the insurer to underwrite the risk, or the replies to questions asked by the insurer, are incomplete or inadequate. This can have a disastrous effect on the validity of the policies and the payment of claims, as will be explained later.

Some basic insurance principles

Insurable interest

A basic principle of insurance law is that before a person can effect an insurance policy, that person must have an insurable interest in the subject matter. This means that the person must suffer some detriment if the subject matter is damaged, or must benefit from its continued well-being. Thus the owner of property is prejudiced if it is lost or stolen.

However, person A cannot insure person B’s property against damage, since in the event of its being lost or stolen, person A has no interest in it. If person A were able to insure person B’s property, person A would clearly benefit by its destruction. The payment of insurance monies to person A would be contrary to public policy and such a policy would be illegal and void.

Disclosure of material facts

Like other forms of contract, insurance is subject to the normal contractual rules of offer and acceptance, consideration (the premium), legality, agreement of the parties, contractual capacity of the parties and the intention to create a legal relationship. Insurance contracts, however, differ fundamentally from other commercial contracts in the sense that they are bound by the principle of utmost good faith. In other words, there is a duty on the insured to disclose to the insurer all facts material to the risk which are known to the insured and not to the insurer.

A material fact is one which would have had an effect (although not necessarily decisive) on the mind of a prudent underwriter, not necessarily the one who agreed the policy, in agreeing to accept the risk or not, or in deciding the amount of premium to charge. Whether or not the insured considered the fact to be material is not relevant. It is a test of the prudent underwriter, not the prudent insured. If there is a non-disclosure of a material fact and if the insurer can show that the underwriter was induced to agree to issue a policy on its relevant terms, the insurer may avoid the policy ab initio — from inception. In practice the requirement to show inducement is satisfied where the insurer can prove either that the policy would not have been issued or that the policy terms would have been different, had there been full and proper disclosure.

The insured has a duty to disclose all material facts within his knowledge, whether actual or presumed, which have a bearing on the risk proposed and must make no misrepresentation about those facts or the risk. This includes all those facts which in the ordinary course of business affairs the insured knows or ought to have known about.

Insurers often insist upon a proposal form being completed before insurance is offered. This asks a number of relevant questions which are material to the risk. The important point to note is that even though a question is not asked, if there is something material to the risk then the insured must disclose it. Moreover, most proposal forms contain a declaration and warranty at the foot of the form, to be signed by the insured, affirming that he has answered all questions accurately and not withheld material information. The effect of signing this declaration and warranty is that the insured warrants the accuracy of all the answers on the proposal form and further warrants that there has been no withholding of, or failure to disclose, material facts. A warranty in insurance law must be strictly complied with; in the event of a breach of warranty the policy, depending upon its terms, will either be void from the date of the breach or be voidable ad initio, at the discretion of the insurer, regardless of whether the breach gives rise to a loss or claim. Any inaccuracy in the proposal form is a breach of warranty which gives an insurer the right to treat the policy as void ab initio. Hence the importance of making sure that all answers to questions and information shown on proposal forms are correct.

Over the years many technical and legal rules have been established in reaction to non-disclosure. Generally the following will be held to be material and must, therefore, be disclosed:

facts indicating that the subject matter of the insurance is exposed to more than the ordinary degree of risk, e.g. that the works are being constructed in an area particularly susceptible to flooding which might not otherwise be apparent from other information supplied;
facts indicating that the insured is activated by some special motive as, for example, where the value of property is greatly over-stated. In the absence of explanation, over-insurance may be indicative of an intent to create a loss with a view to a claim on the policy;
facts showing that the liability of the insurer is greater than would normally have been expected, e.g. that very valuable property is contained in a building with a poor standard of security and in an area where there has been a high incidence of theft;
facts showing that there is a moral hazard attaching to the insured suggesting that he is not a fit person to whom insurance can be granted, e.g. a person with a bad criminal history, particularly if it involves dishonesty, arson or reckless behaviour;
facts which to the insured’s knowledge are regarded by the insurers as material, such as high incidence of theft on a contract site.

On the other hand there are facts which, although material, may become immaterial in certain circumstances and there is, therefore, no obligation upon the insured to disclose them. For example:

facts which are already known to the insurer or which the insurer may be reasonably presumed to know, e.g. that work at height or depth is hazardous;
facts which the insurer could have discovered by making some enquiries; for example, if the insurer is told that demolition work is to be carried out, the insurer has the opportunity to investigate the risks involved if required;
facts where the insurer has waived further information, where for example the insurer is told that a certain contractor is being used to perform the work and that contractor is known to be unsatisfactory;
facts tending to lessen the risk — for obvious reasons, since anything that lessens the risk is beneficial to the underwriter.

Contracts of indemnity

Insurance contracts are contracts of indemnity under which the insurer agrees to make good the insured’s loss by payment, repair, reinstatement or some other method. The principle of indemnity is that the insured should be neither better nor worse off after the occurrence of an insured event but (in so far as a sum of money can do so) should be placed in exactly the same position as if the event insured against had not happened. If property worth £500 is lost then the insurer pays £500 to the insured. The insured is thus indemnified. Even if insured for £900 the insured still gets £500. To give the insured more than the loss is to encourage the insured to bring about the insured event. The onus of seeing that the sum insured is correct is on the insured.

Subrogation and contribution

The matter of indemnity is subject to two important principles known as subrogation and contribution.

Subrogation means that where an insured has been indemnified, then the insurer can stand in the insured’s shoes and avail himself of all rights and remedies open to the insured. In other words, if the isnsured’s property worth £500 has been damaged by negligence of a third party, the insurer will pay £500 to the insured. The insured will have been indemnified. By subrogation the insurer is then entitled, in the insured’s name, to sue the third party to recover the £500.

Contribution applies where the same interest and the same risk are insured by more than one policy. In that case both policies contribute towards the loss in accordance with certain legal principles. The insured cannot recover the loss in full under each of the policies, as that would defeat the principle of indemnity.

Joint insurance and co-insurance

Joint insurance arises where two or more insureds have the same interest in the subject matter of the insurance, for example joint owners of a piece of land or land and buildings.

Co-insurance arises where two or more insureds have different interests in the same property, for example it has been decided by the courts, in Petrofina v. Magnaload (1983) that a main contractor and sub-contractor are co-insureds. The significance is that in joint insurance a breach of duty by one joint insured will entitle an insurer to avoid the policy against all joint insureds, whereas a breach of duty by one co-insured entities an insurer to avoid the policy only against the co-insured in breach; the policy remains valid and subsisting for co-insured not in breach of duty.

It should be noted that reference later in this text to a policy being ‘in the joint names of a Contractor and Employer’ is a reference to co-insurance and not joint insurance, as their respective interests in the subject matter of the insurance are different.

Layout of a typical insurance policy

A typical insurance policy consists principally of policy wording and a policy schedule. Detailed provisions are dealt with in later chapters dealing with specific types of policy.

The wording is what one might call the ‘standard terms’ of the insurance, although in practice it is not uncommon for the wording to be specially drafted or tailored to suit the needs of a particular insured. Where the wording is not the ‘standard’ product of an insurer or insurance broker, it is often referred to as a ‘bespoke wording’.

The wording is likely to include the following:

The insuring clause: the words used to describe the nature of the insurance. In the typical Public Liability policy in Appendix 1 and Employer’s Liability policy in Appendix 2, the insuring clause is in Section 2. In the typical Contract Works policy in Appendix 3, it is in Section 1. The insuring clause often shows with whom lies the burden of proof that a valid claim exists: in all ‘all-risks’ policy (e.g. Appendix 3 — referring to ‘loss or damage however caused’) the insured need prove only unintended damage. The burden of proof then shifts to the insurer to prove an exclusion or other provision which may exclude or limit the insurer’s liability. In contrast, the insuring clauses in the typical policies in Appendices 1 and 2 describe the subject of the policy cover, and the initial burden of proof is upon the insured to show that the claim is within the description in the insuring clause.
Extensions: these are additions to the basic cover provided by a policy and may be referred to as ‘memoranda’, ‘endorsements’ (as in Appendix 1), or simply as ‘extensions’ (as in Appendix 3).
Exclusions (also called ‘exceptions’): examples appear in the typical policies. The burden of proof is upon an insurer to establish that a risk or claim is excluded by this type of provision.
Warranties: the typical policies given in the Appendices do not include examples of express warranties. In these types of policy a warranty will usually relate to the conduct of an insured when undertaking a particular task. For example, a contractor who often uses flame-cutting equipment may be required to warrant that when so doing there will be fire extinguishers within easy reach, a fire-watch will be maintained and the area will be checked for combustible materials before work begins. As already mentioned,warranties have particular significance in insurance law and must be strictly complied with.
Conditions: there are three basic kinds of policy condition:

A condition precedent to the policy, breach of which renders the policy voidable ab initio at the discretion of the insurer. An example would be a breach of the duty of utmost good faith, such as a failure to disclose material information.
A condition subsequent to the policy may render the policy voidable from the date of the breach. An example would be a change in the risk so that it is different from that which the underwriter thought he was covering. The policy is effective for all claims up to the date of the change but not thereafter.
A condition precedent to liability is one which must be observed before the insurer becomes liable under the policy. This kind of condition does not affect the validity of the policy but may affect the right of an insured to indemnity for a particular claim. For example, a condition requiring a contractor to notify claims within a stated time, if breached, may entitle an insurer to reject a claim.

The schedule of a policy will contain details specific to the subject being insured. The typical policies outlined in the Appendices provide examples of the details given in such schedules.

2 The basis of legal liability for personal injury or damage to third party property

Accidents on construction projects are not uncommon. People are injured or their property is damaged. Those people, however, have no automatic right to obtain damages from those who caused the injury or damage. They must first prove legal liability (fault).

How liability arises

There are several ways in which legal liability may attach to the defendant. They include:

negligence;
nuisance;
trespass;
breach of statutory duty;
strict liability;
liability under contract; and
vicarious liability.

Other than liability under contract, these forms of liability are referred to as torts, i.e. civil wrongs independent of contract. This Chapter describes some of the legal issues involved in order to understand how liability arises, how it may be excluded, modified, apportioned or transferred under appropriate clauses in a building or engineering contract and the extent of cover available under legal liability insurance policies.

Negligence

Negligence produces most claims. Negligence is omitting to do something which a reasonable and prudent person would do, or doing something which a prudent and reasonable person would not do. Negligence on its own, however, will not bring liability. The sole occupant of an island can be as negligent as he wishes since there is no other person at risk. It is only when other persons or property are at risk that there is a duty of care not to be negligent.

To succeed in an action for negligence a plaintiff must prove:

that the defendant owed the plaintiff a duty of care;
that the defendant breached that duty of care; and
that the plaintiff suffered injury or damage as a result of the breach.

Duty of care

A defendant owes a duty of care to those whom he ought reasonably to have in mind at the time of carrying out activities. This is the ‘neighbour’ principle, established in the case of Donoghue v. Stephenson (1932), where Lord Atkin answering the question ‘Who in law is my neighbour?’ said, ‘Persons who are so closely and directly affected by my act that I ought reasonably to have them in contemplation as being so affected when I am directing my mind to the acts or omissions which are called in question’.

Whether there is a duty of care at any particular time is a question of law to be decided by the court.

Reasonable care

The extent of the duty of care depends upon reasonable foresight and reasonable care. A defendant will owe a duty of care to those persons whom he can reasonably foresee may be injured by his acts or omissions but the defendant will only breach a duty of care if, reasonably foreseeing the risk of loss or damage to a neighbour, he does not take reasonable care to avoid it. For instance, if a defendant knows of loose tiles on a roof of his own property, he owes a duty of care to prevent them falling and causing third party injury or damage. The standard of ‘reasonable care’ is an objective one, being that of the ordinary reasonable person in the circumstances of the case.

The burden of proving negligence rests upon the plaintiff, except where the principle of res ipsa loquitur (the thing speaks of itself) applies. If a sack of flour falls out of a building on to an innocent bystander res ipsa loquitur applies. In the natural order of things, sacks of flour ought not to fall out of buildings. Negligence is therefore presumed against the defendant, to whom the onus of disproving it passes. The defendant may rebut the presumption by showing that the accident occurred without any negligence on his part.

Even though a person may be negligent, a plaintiff will not succeed if his injury or damage was too remote, i.e. if there is not a sufficient causal link between the act of negligence and the injury, loss or damage suffered. For example, a motorist who injures a child on holiday will not generally be liable for the shock to the mother at home or when she is told the news several days later. From the defendant’s point of view the injury to the mother is too remote; it is too far removed from the act of negligence to create liability.

Further, a plaintiff will not succeed with a claim for ‘pure economic loss’, which is a loss which does not arise from physical damage to the plaintiffs tangible property; for example, a plaintiff cannot claim in negligence for an undamaged building that will not carry its expected loadings due to an error or omission of the defendant. This does not apply where the defendant is guilty of a negligent mis-statement. In Hedley Byrne v. Heller & Partners (1963) the House of Lords decided that where a statement is made by one party to another and there is a ‘special relationship’ between the parties, the maker of the statement owes a duty to act with reasonable skill and care. The ‘special relationship’ is a combination of one party having knowledge which the other does not and the reliance of the other upon the mis-statement.

Nuisance

Nuisance is a wrong done to someone by creating noise, smells, dust or vibrations, thus unlawfully disturbing that person in the enjoyment of property or, in some cases, in the exercise of a right such as a right of way or a right to light. The basic principle of the law relating to nuisance is that a person must use property in a way that does not cause harm to others.

A public nuisance is a crime. A nuisance will not be a public one unless the number of persons affected is substantially large enough to constitute a ‘class’ of persons, e.g. a large number of people affected by blasting and quarrying operations near their homes. A public nuisance is only actionable as a civil claim if a plaintiff can show that particular damage was suffered over and above that suffered by the rest of the public at large.

A private nuisance is an interference over a period of time by owners or occupiers of property with the use and enjoyment by others of neighbouring property. A private nuisance can consist of allowing the escape of noxious things such as smoke, smells, noise, gas, vibration, damp and so on, so as to interfere with the health, comfort or convenience of neighbours in the enjoyment of their property, or the wrongful disturbance of rights attached to land, such as a right to light and air, rights to support of land and buildings and rights in respect of water and rivers. Liability for such disturbances of rights attaching to land is strict, i.e. without proof of negligence.

Nuisance and negligence may overlap. Although some actions in nuisance arise from intentional acts, some also arise from a defendant’s inadvertence and in these cases the plaintiff may sue in nuisance or negligence.

Trespass

Trespass is an unlawful act committed on the person, property or right of another. The essence of trespass is the direct injury. Indirect injuries fall within the areas of negligence or nuisance. Trespass is a strict tort and is actionable per se, that is without proof of special damage (particular financial loss). It is a trespass for a contractor to go on to another person’s land without lawful authority, even if he causes no damage; the injury is the entry on to the land without permission or lawful excuse.

Trespass may be of three kinds — to land, to goods and to the person.

Trespass to land

An unlawful entry on to land or buildings in the possession of another is trespass. If a person remains on the land or allows things he has unlawfully placed on the land to remain there, such trespass can be the subject of a fresh action for each day that it continues. Trespass in such circumstances is a continuing trespass. A possessor of land possesses the soil beneath and the claim of air above it. As a consequence, an occupier may remove things trespassing into the overlying air space even though they do no harm, e.g. overhanging branches or tower cranes. Trespass may also be restrained by injunction; for obvious reasons those engaged in civil engineering must take care that the works do not encroach on to the land of others.

Trespass to goods

Trespass to goods consists of a direct and unlawful injury to or interference with goods in the possession of another.

The point about possession is essential because it is the sole basis of the plaintiffs right. Only the person in possession of the goods at the time of the trespass can bring the action.

Trespass to a person

Trespass to a person consists of assault or battery or false imprisonment. Battery is the application of unlawful force to the person of another. Assault is putting a person in reasonable fear of immediate battery.

Breach of statutory duty

Acts of Parliament often contain regulations designed to prevent injury to persons or damage to property, or to give to persons the legal right to sue for a breach of the regulations contained in the legislation. Examples are requirements of the Factories Acts, the Construction Regulations, the Health & Safety at Work etc. Act, the Building Regulations, the Occupier’s Liability Act, the Fatal Accidents Act and the Mines & Quarries Acts. Although such legislation may lay down criminal sanctions (e.g. fines), a breach of any duty by the defendant under such legislation may be actionable in civil law by the person who is injured., The success of the claim will depend on the construction of the words of the statute. Thus if there is a statutory duty to fence dangerous machinery, a failure to fence will be a breach of the duty and the breach may be absolute. Alternatively, legislation may require fencing ‘in so far as it is reasonable or practical to do so’. This is not absolute and an investigation would need to be made into whether the fencing at the material time was reasonable or practicable. In other words, the risk has to be balanced against the practicability of the measures needed to avoid it. Cost, for example, has to be taken into account.

The burden of proof that there has been a breach of statutory duty is upon the plaintiff. The standard of proof required in civil actions is proof upon a balance of probability. In addition, a plaintiff must prove:

that a breach of the duty caused injury, in other words that there was a causal link. For example, a steel erector fell and was killed because he was not wearing a safety belt in accordance with statutory regulations. It was the practice of steel erectors never to wear belts; thus if belts had been available it was improbable that the deceased would have worn one. The claim failed, as the breach of duty did not cause the accident.
that the plaintiff was one of a class of persons the statute was intended to protect. For example, an engine driver was injured when a car ran into a level crossing gate which had not been maintained in accordance with the statutory requirements. His claim failed because the purpose of the Act was to protect road users, not engine drivers.
that the injury of which the plaintiff complains is one the statute was intended to prevent. For example, a plaintiff’s sheep were washed overboard because the defendant had failed to provide pens on the ship’s deck as required by statute. The claim failed. The object of the statute was to prevent the spread of disease among sheep, not to prevent them from being washed overboard.

Negligence and breach of statutory duty are usually regarded as two distinct claims even though there may be some overlapping – for example, where the statutory duty is to ‘take all such circumstances as in the case are reasonable’. In negligence the standard of care is decided by the court, whereas in breach of statutory duty the standard of care is actually laid down in the statute.

Strict liability

A defendant may have liabilities imposed by law which cannot be avoided even with the exercise of reasonable care and skill. The liability is said therefore to be strict, since it does not require proof of negligence or lack of care or wrongful intention. Strict liability can occur in the cirumstances such as those covered by the rule in Rylands v. Fletcher (1868) (liability for escape of dangerous things on defendant’s land). In that case, an employer engaged an independent contractor to construct a reservoir on the employer’s land. Unknown to the employer, there were disused mine shafts on the site and when the reservoir was filled the plaintiffs adjoining coal mine was flooded. The employer was held liable since the court held that ‘any person who for his own purposes brings on his land and collects and keeps there anything likely to do mischief if it escapes must keep it at his peril and if he does not do so it is prima facie answerable for all the damage which is the natural consequences of its escape’.

Whether a ‘thing’ which has been brought on to the defendant’s land is one which is likely to do mischief if it escapes is a question of fact. A wide variety of things have been held to be within the Rylands v. Fletcher rule, such as electricity, gas, sewage and vibration.

For the rule to apply there must be an escape from the ‘defendant’s land of the ‘thing likely to do mischief’ and there must have been a non-natural use of the defendant’s land. In one case the defendant had explosives on his land. The plaintiff, a munitions inspector of the Ministry of Supply, was injured, while on the premises, by an explosion. He had no claim under the Rylands v. Fletcher rule since his injuries had taken place on the land. There had been no escape from the land of the dangerous thing. Also there must be a non-natural use of the land, so things naturally on the land, such as weeds, are not within the rule.

Animals

The Animals Act 1971 codified the previous common law relating to animals.

There is a strict liability for injury caused by dangerous animals (defined as fully grown animals which, unless restrained, are likely to cause severe damage). The liability is imposed on the ‘keeper’, i.e. the owner or the person who had the animal in his possession.

Guard dogs on contract sites could come within the rule. Trespass by cattle may also be strict.

Fire

Strict liability may attach to certain forms of damage arising out of fire, and liability for fire is often governed by the rule in Rylands v. Fletcher or by statute.

An employer is liable for fire damage caused by the negligence of his independent contractors. In Balfour v. Barty-King (1956), the occupier of a house engaged contractors to thaw her water pipes. They used blowlamps and set fire to the house. The fire spread to the neighbouring house, causing damage. The occupier was held liable.

Product liability

The Consumer Protection Act 1987 introduced strict liability on producers of goods which are defective, causing personal injury or damage to personal property.

Liability under contract

Liability under the torts considered previously is a liability imposed upon the parties by law. Under the terms and conditions of written contracts, liabilities are imposed upon or accepted by the parties voluntarily by the terms of that contract. Thus parties may add to or detract from their liability in tort. Such contracts often contain indemnity clauses of the types seen in the ICE Conditions of Contract, where the liability of the parties may be widened.

Vicarious liability

An employer has vicarious liability for the acts or omissions of employees and, in some circumstances, for his/her independent contractors. First of all, it is necessary to recognise that there is a distinction in law between an employee, who is a person employed under a contract of service, and an independent contractor, who is a person employed under a contract for services.

An independent contractor is a person engaged by the employer to produce a given result where the employer has no power to direct the method of doing the work. This is left to the discretion of the independent contractor, who has the necessary skills. On the other hand, an employee is usually subject to the control of the employer and must follow instructions.

An employer is normally vicariously liable for the activities of employees because the employer has the power of control over them and thus will be liable for their acts or omissions during the course of their employment. The employer is not, as a matter of general principle, liable for the activities of independent contractors since normally the control factor is missing. There are, however, important exceptions to this principle and the employer may be liable for the acts of independent contractors if the liability arises from the work itself. In these circumstances the employer is under a strict duty to avoid injury or damage. The following examples illustrate such circumstances.

Where the work involved ‘extra-hazardous’ operations. The defendant was engaged by the plaintiff to take flashlight photographs in a third party cinema. The defendant negligently caused fire for which the plaintiff had to compensate the cinema owner. The court held that the plaintiff could recover this amount from the defendant because the plaintiff was liable to the cinema owner for the independent contractor’s extra-hazardous act.

Work in connection with the withdrawal of support to land or buildings would come under the ‘extra-hazardous work’ definition. So too would work which is being performed on or close to a highway, e.g. a demolition contract.

Where a contractor is employed to do illegal or unlawful work. The defendant engaged a contractor to dig trenches in the street, without obtaining the necessary authority. The plaintiff fell over stones left by the contractor and the defendant was held liable.
Where a measure of control over a contractor is retained by an employer through the provision of machinery or men. Subcontractors were used to discharge ships. The employer provided equipment to enable them to do this. People engaged by the sub-contractors were injured. The employer was held liable because of the employer’s retention of a sufficient degree of control over the workmen by the provision of the equipment.
Where an employer is under a statutory duty to perform work in a particular way. The defendants were engaged by an employer to construct a bridge across a river but were restricted by statute to a requirement that the bridge should not detain any vessel using the river longer than was necessary. The bridge could not be opened for several days because the independent contractor did not do the job properly. The employer was held liable.
Where the negligence is that of an employer using an inexperienced or incompetent contractor or failing to give sufficient instructions. An employer was held responsible for the activities of a contractor who had deposited sewage from a cleaning contract on to another person’s land. It was adjudged that the employer should have taken more care to see that the contractor disposed of the sewage correctly.

For an employer to be liable, the tortious activities of an independent contractor must be ones upon which the contractor is employed to work and not merely ancillary acts connected with it. In other words, an employer is not liable for what is known as the ‘collateral negligence’ of an independent contractor. In one case the defendant was a main contractor. A sub-contractor injured the plaintiff by carelessly leaving a tool on a window sill from which it fell on to the plaintiff. The court held that the main contractor could not be held liable for the simple collateral negligence of the sub-contractor.

Defences

Several defences to a claim may be open to a defendant; these are as follows.

Denial

The obvious one is that of denial, i.e. the defendant denies that, on the facts, the acts or omissions complained of amount to negligence or breach of any duty owed to the plaintiff.

Inevitable accident

It is a defence to some torts that an accident has taken place despite the exercise of all reasonable care on the part of the defendant. If the defence is that the accident was inevitable, it is another way of saying that the defendant has not failed in any duty to observe the standards of care expected of him. Thus a contractor may blame the employer because the accident was the inevitable result of undertaking the works for the employer.

Act of God

This is a defence limited to torts involving strict liability, such as the rule in Rylands v. Fletcher. An Act of God is an event that is due to natural consequences directly and exclusively without human intervention and that could not have been prevented by any amount of foresight and care. (Incidentally the view that insurance policies do not cover Acts of God is wrong. They do.)

Emergency action

A defence may be that actions were taken in an emergency and were therefore reasonable in all the circumstances – as, for example, where a motorist swerves to avoid a young child running into the road.

Contributory negligence

Where a plaintiff is partly to blame for an injury or damage, the recoverable damages will be scaled down accordingly; for example, if a plaintiff is 30% to blame, damages are reduced by 30%.

Volenti non fit injuria

A literal translation is ‘to him who is willing there can be no injury’. In other words, a person consenting to undergo a risk cannot later sue if, as a consequence of running the risk, injury or damage was sustained. The consent, however, must be real. A person cannot be taken to have consented to a risk if the nature of that risk was not really understood, e.g. a boxer accepts the risk of injury but not if his opponent has weights in his gloves.

Limitation of action

There are time limits for bringing claims prescribed by legislation. If the claim is not brought within the appropriate time limit, then the defendant may argue that the claim is time-barred.

Statutory authority

Where a statute specifically authorises a certain act to be done, injury or damage arising out of the performance of that act may carry with it statutory exemption from liability. For example, in the early days of steam locomotives the railway companies were exempted from liability for fires caused by escaping sparks. It is a question of interpretation of the words of the appropriate statute as to whether it gives total exemption or partial exemption, i.e. so as not to cover the negligent performance of the statutory function.

Act of a stranger

The true cause of injury of damage may not be that of the defendant’s but of a third party over whom the defendant has no control. For example, a third party discharged water into the defendant’s reservoir so that it overflowed and damaged a plaintiff’s property. The court held that the defendant was not liable, under the principle of Rylands v. Fletcher.

Conclusions

This brief review of the basis of liability is very much an oversimplification, but it shows that there is a complex system of legal rules involved in deciding liability and the extent to which damages will be paid.

The extent to which contracting parties may agree between themselves how such liability will be handled and apportioned is determined by appropriate clauses in the construction contract. This is considered in the next chapter.

The fact that a person may be insured does not affect liability. Insurance cannot change the law, it may merely provide money to meet some or all of the financial consequences of liability. The extent (if any) of the insured’s legal liability has to be investigated and determined, if necessary by the courts. If there is no legal liability, then there is nothing against which an insurer needs to indemnify an insured. If there is legal liability, the insurer will pay the claim on behalf of the insured up to the limit of indemnity provided by the policy.

4 Requirement for third party liability insurance

It has been described already how a Contractor and/or an Employer (and others) might face liability claims for death or injury to persons (employees and third parties) or damage to third party property. However, there is little point in making claims against persons who lack the financial resources to deal with them. Therefore, to reduce the vulnerability of the Employer to claims which should fairly rest wholly or partly with a Contractor (who may not have the financial resources to support any indemnity given), there are requirements in ICE Conditions of Contract for a Contractor to take out insurance to cover liabilities. Those requirements are described in the following paragraphs.

ICE 6,Clause 23

Wording of Clause 23(1) — Third party insurance

‘The Contractor shall without limiting his or the Employer’s obligations and responsibilities under Clause 22 insure in the joint names of the Contractor and the Employer against liabilities for death of or injury to any person (other than any operative or other person in the employment of the Contractor or any of his sub-contractors) or loss of or damage to any property (other than the Works) arising out of the performance of the Contract other than those due to the exceptions defined in Clause 22(2)(a)(b)(c) and (d)’.

Commentary on Clause 23(1)

The insurance required under this Clause is for a Contractor’s third party public liability only. It excludes persons engaged by a Contractor and a Contractor’s sub-contractors, it excludes the Works, and it excludes exceptions (a) to (d) given in Clause 22(2), which are the responsibility of the Employer. (However, interestingly the Contractor’s third party liability insurance does not exclude (i.e. does include) the exception given in Clause 22(2)(e) — injury or damage due to an Employer’s neglect or breach of statutory duty. This appears to be a particularly onerous liability for a Contractor!) Although the policy must, according to Clause 23(1), be in the joint names of the Contractor and Employer, which thus enables the Employer to obtain third party cover under the Contractor’s policy, it is a case of coinsurance and not joint insurance. It also enables one party, such as the Employer, to make a claim on insurers even if the other party is unwilling to do so. However, public liability cover excludes injury to persons employed by the insured or damage to property of the insured, and therefore injury or damage caused by one insured party to the other insured would normally be excluded. This is overcome by ICE 6 also requiring a cross liability clause (see Clause 23(2), discussed below).

The implications of Clause 23(1) read in conjunction with Clause 22(1) are that insurance should be required to meet all losses and claims in respect of death or injury to any third party or damage to any third party property. However, a public liability policy does not cover all forms of damage to all property. The policy has limitations in extent of cover (e.g. it will have bottomend deductibles or excesses, and perhaps top-end ceilings per claim and annual limits), and exclusions (e.g. it will exclude injury or damage arising from radioactivity from any nuclear fuel (uninsurable in the commercial insurance market)), it will exclude injury arising from motor vehicles used on the road (for which compulsory motor insurance is required) and it will exclude liability arising out of the use of aircraft, ships or other vessels.

Seldom do the policies issued by insurers correspond exactly with the requirements of conditions of contract. A detailed analysis is therefore necessary by both Contractor and Employer to see what the deficiencies are in the Public Liability policy and whether those deficiencies are insured under other policies.

An Employer needs to be satisfied that a Contractor’s indemnity can be adequately financed if called upon. A Contractor also needs to be satisfied that indemnity obligations can be met, as liability remains whether or not insurance is in place. Complexities can arise because cover can be provided by a pre-agreed annual renewable Contractor’s policy, by a project policy, by a Contractor’s own captive insurance company, by a group of ‘lead’ and ‘following’ insurers or reinsurers, by a complicated risk financing programme including insured and self-insured portions, and so on. In many situations parties may need to obtain specialist advice to ensure that adequate indemnity provisions are actually being supplied.

Wording of Clause 23(2) — Cross liability

‘The insurance policy shall include a cross liability clause such that the insurance shall apply to the Contractor and to the Employer as separate insured’.

Commentary on Clause 23(2)

A cross liability clause enables the third party policy to be treated as if a separate policy has been issued to each of the parties, i.e. as if each party is a third party as far as the other is concerned. For example, if a joint-named Contractor damages a joint-named Employer’s property (other than the Works), because of the cross liability clause indemnity can be claimed by the Employer from the Contractor under the joint names policy.

Wording of Clause 23(3) — Amount of insurance

‘Such insurance shall be for at least the amount stated in the Appendix to the Form of Tender.’

Commentary on Clause 23(3)

The limit stated in the Appendix will be a minimum selected by an Employer, probably with the advice of others such as professional advisors. However, a Contractor will have unlimited liability in law and must determine what level of cover is required from the Public Liability insurance. The Contractor should undertake a risk assessment of possible hazardous events which might impact on third parties — to find out the financial implications, the possibilities of occurrence, what non-insured portion (e.g. deductible) needs to be covered by means other than insurance, the implications and exposures of other works being undertaken by the Contractor, and so on. In addition to these aspects, liability may be decided some years after a contract has been completed and the effects of inflation need to be taken into account. It must also be borne in mind that the extent of exposure bears no relationship to the contract value, with even small contracts producing large claims.

ICE Design and Construct,Clause 23

The wording is identical to Clause 23 of ICE 6.

ICE Minor Works,Clause 10.6

Wording of Clause 10.6 — Employer to approve insurance

‘The Contractor shall throughout the execution of the Works maintain insurance against damage loss or injury for which he is liable under Clause 10.2 subject to the exceptions provided by Clauses 10.3 and 10.4. ⋯ The terms of such insurance shall include a provision whereby in the event of any claim in respect of which the Contractor would be entitled to receive indemnity under the policy being brought or made against the Employer the insurer will indemnify the Employer against any such claims and any costs charges and expenses in respect thereof.

Commentary on Clause 10.6

It will be noted that unlike ICE 6, third party insurance is not in the joint names of the Contractor and Employer, nor is there a cross liability clause. Because the Employer is not, strictly speaking, a party to the policy, where a third party sues an Employer for an issue where the Contractor would be liable, the Employer cannot sue the insurer directly for indemnity. In practice an insurer will indemnify the Employer where the Contractor is liable and hence entitled to indemnity. If, however, the Employer was liable to a third party in circumstances where the Contractor was not liable, the Employer would be uninsured.

The Guidance Notes to ICE Minor Works advise a minimum limit of indemnity of £2 million for any one accident/unlimited number of accidents and an even higher limit at locations of greater risks. This is because, although the value of the Works may be small, the risk to third parties may be the same as for higher-value contracts.

NEC,Clause 84 — Insurance cover

Clause 84 in part relates to insurance to cover a Contractor’s liability for personal injury and damage to third party property.

Wording of Clause 84.1

‘The Contractor provides the insurances stated in the Insurance Table except any insurance which the Employer is to provide as stated in the Contract Data. The Contractor provides additional insurances as stated in the Contract Data.’

Insurance Table

Insurance against | Minimum amount of cover or minimum limit of indemnity
Liability for loss of or damage to property (except the works, Plant and Materials and Equipment) and liability for bodily injury to or death of a person (not an employee of the Contractor) caused by activity in connection with this contract. | The amount stated in the Contract Data for any one event with cross liability so that the insurance applies to the Parties separately.

Wording of Clause 84.2

‘The insurances are in the joint names of the Parties and provide cover for events which are due to the Contractor’s risk from the starting date until the Defects Certificate has been issued.’

Contract Data Part one — Data provided by the Employer

Paragraph 8 in part relates to Employer requirements for the Contractor’s insurance cover of liabilities to third parties. The relevant part-wording is:

‘The amount of the minimum limit of indemnity for insurance in respect of loss of or damage to property (except the works, Plant and Materials and Equipment) and liability for bodily injury to or death of a person (not an employee of the Contractor) due to activity in connection with this contract for any one event is ..........’.

One of the ‘Optional Statements’ enables the Employer, instead of the Contractor, to provide insurance against third party liabilities. It requires the Employer to fill in details of the indemnity to be provided and any applicable deductibles.

Commentary on Clauses 84.1 and 84.2 and Paragraph 8 of the Contract Data

The Contractor must provide insurance against liability for third party injury or death to persons or loss of or damage to property, unless the Employer has stated in the Contract Data that the Employer will provide that insurance. The insurance covers persons who are employees of the Employer, and property (other than the works) which belongs to the Employer.

The Employer states the minimum amount of cover required per event. Paragraph 8 appears to require one amount, whether the event applies to persons or property. A site in a remote overseas location might require a different property indemnity from one in the centre of a Western city. In addition, the value of property indemnity might be totally different from the indemnity required for liability for injury or death to persons. The Employer should therefore consider for his project whether giving two indemnity values in Paragraph 8 is more appropriate, i.e. one for persons and one for property.

Where the Contractor is providing third party property insurance, no limit is placed on the deductible permitted; however, where the Employer is providing cover instead, a deductible is stated.

The insurance is a joint names policy with cross liability. (It will be apparent from Chapter 1 that the insureds are, in insurance terms, co-insureds, not joint-insureds.) As described earlier, the cross liability permits the cover to apply to the Employer’s employees or property (excluding the works) where injury or damage is caused by the Contractor, even though the Employer is named as an insured in the policy.

5 A Contractor’s Public Liability policy

The liability of a Contractor for causing injury to third parties or damage to third party property is covered by the Contractor’s Public Liability policy (sometimes called a Third Party policy).

Policies vary from insurer to insurer. Some specialise in contractor’s insurances, others do not. In practice there is much variation in the cover given by policies and there is no such thing as a standard Public Liability policy.

A specimen policy is included in Appendix 1. It is intended to be typical of the type of policy which is met in practice. For ease of reference, the various parts of the policy have been given numbered section headings in the Appendix and these section numbers are referred to in the following text.

Section 1 – The opening clause

This is a typical opening clause to an insurance policy. There are a number of important points to note.

The premium charged by an insurer and the extent of cover an insurer is prepared to give are geared to the business to be insured. It is important, therefore, to see that the business is adequately described. A policy describing the insured simply as a building contractor, for example, would not insure against liabilities arising during civil engineering work on bridges. A policy showing the insured as a painting contractor would not insure against liabilities arising during demolition work.
An insurer obtains underwriting information (the basis for the decision whether or not to accept the risk and the amount of premium) from information supplied by or on behalf of an insured in proposing the risk. The proposal, which may include a proposal form if required by the insurer, will almost certainly include information about the contractor’s business in the case of annual covers or about the proposed works in the case of project cover. Any inaccuracies in the proposal may give an insurer a right to avoid the policy. Hence the proposal form and any other information should be completed with great care and a copy of it always retained for future reference.
The premium is the contract ‘consideration’ for which the insurer agrees to enter into the insurance contract and to issue the policy.

Section 2 – The insuring clause

This is the insuring clause of the policy setting out the cover. The following are the important points to note.

The cover is subject to the other terms, exceptions, limits and conditions set out in the policy. In other words, the document has to be read as a whole.
The insurer agrees to indemnify the insured against the insured’s legal liability. In other words, the insurer will stand in the insured’s shoes, negotiate on the insured’s behalf and pay any damages as may be necessary. The insured is usually a limited liability company or partnership. Many policies extend the definition to include directors and employees of the insured so that they too are protected by the policy for their activities in connection with the business.
The cover is to pay all sums which the insured shall become legally liable to pay. As explained in Chapter 2, legal liability can arise in many circumstances including negligence, nuisance, trespass, strict liability, liability under statute and contractual liability. It is a legal liability policy, not one covering moral liabilities or liabilities voluntarily incurred for business or other reasons.
The promise is to pay any damages awarded against the insured, i.e. the amount of compensation to which the claimant is entitled. (In practice most claims are settled by negotiation. Few go to court.)
The damages must relate to a claimant’s injury or damage and must be awarded ‘in respect of that injury or damage. Thus the policy will protect the insured against the insured’s liability for injury or damage sustained directly by the claimant plus any consequential losses which may flow from that injury or damage. In other words, if a claimant’s house is badly damaged and the claimant incurs costs in staying in an hotel while the repairs are carried out, the policy will pay for the damage to the house plus the necessary hotel expenses and any other consequential losses flowing from the damage.
The policy protects against liability for bodily injury to third parties which includes death, illness, accident and disease.
The policy protects against liability in respect of loss or damage to property and losses consequent upon such damage. The term ‘property’ is capable of a wide meaning and can include both tangible and intangible property. The intention of most insurers is to cover only damage to tangible property and liability for interference with the rights of others by, for instance, obstructing the highway, trespassing, causing excessive dust or noise, restricting use or enjoyment of rights of way, light and water. What the policy is not intended to cover is loss of or damage to intellectual property (patents, copyright, designs, etc.) and it may contain an express exclusion to that effect.
The policy operates only if the injury or damage is accidental. Injury or damage which is inevitable, unavoidable or deliberate is not covered. The intention is to construe the word ‘accidental’ from the insured’s point of view which, in the case of a limited liability company, means the viewpoint of the directors and senior management. It is not the intention to construe the word from an employee’s point of view; for example, reckless conduct by an employee may result in damage which, although not accidental from his or her point of view, is from that of the employer. In practice, difficulties can arise in interpretation.

Injury or damage is accidental when it is the unexpected or unlooked-for consequence of an untoward event which is not expected or designed. In other words it must be fortuitous, as for example when an excavator damages an underground cable because the operator did not know it was there. But if the insured knew its location and took no precautions, the damage would not be accidental. The inevitable consequences of damage by vibration during pile driving, concussion damage arising out of the use of explosives, and dust arising from demolition sites are not accidental.

In some policies the word ‘accidental’ may be omitted by insurers. Nevertheless the intention of the insurers is only to pay for fortuitous damage and one will find an exclusion elsewhere in the policy excluding damage which arises out of the deliberate acts or omissions of the insured or which is inevitable or unavoidable (several different wordings are in use).

The liability and the injury, loss or damage must arise in connection with the business covered by the policy – hence the importance of describing it accurately.
The injury, loss or damage must occur within the territorial limits covered by the policy, e.g. in the United Kingdom. Where work is performed abroad, a special extension to the policy will be required.
The injury, loss or damage must occur during the period of insurance. Once the policy has lapsed there is no cover, even though the events giving rise to the subsequent injury, loss or damage may have occurred during the period of insurance. Thus if structures erected negligently during the period of insurance subsequently collapse and injure a third party after the policy has lapsed, any claim then made will not be covered, because at the date the third party was injured the policy was not in force. Hence a contractor who arranges individual policies for each contract and allows them to lapse when the contract has been finished runs the risk of being uninsured for subsequent injury or damage. If a contractor has an annual policy it is sensible to arrange with insurers to extend that policy to cover this contingent risk.

Section 3 – The limit of indemnity

There is a limit given in a policy up to which the insurer will pay claims, but not beyond. This is known as the limit of indemnity. It is usually a limit per ‘occurrence’. It is important that the insurer describes exactly in what circumstances the limit of indemnity will operate because a great deal is at risk. Thus if there is an ‘occurrence’ (such as an explosion), which injures a great many people, the insurer will not pay more than the limit of indemnity, no matter how many claimants there may be. If the limit is £1 million, that represents the maximum exposure. It is £1 million for the ‘occurrence’, not £1 million per claimant.

Sometimes a lower limit of indemnity may apply to certain parts of the policy, e.g. for damage arising out of fire or explosion or for damage to property arising out of vibration or the removal or weakening of support.

A limit of indemnity may also be exposed ‘in the aggregate’ to create an overall limit on the insurer’s exposure in respect of all occurrences during the period of insurance.

The insurer will also pay the legal costs and expenses of litigation incurred in negotiating or defending a claim. In practice these often amount to a substantial amount and are usually paid in addition to the limit of indemnity. In other words, if the limit of indemnity is £1 million and a plaintiffs claim is settled for £1 million, the insurer will in addition pay the legal costs incurred in negotiating settlement of the claim.

Section 4 – Exceptions

Policy exceptions appear frequently in insurance policies for a number of reasons. Some risks may be insured under other policies and are therefore excluded; otherwise there would be a duplication in cover and unnecessary overpayment of premium. Some risks are excluded because the insurer is not prepared to cover them at all, or unless there is further underwriting information. Other risks are excluded because they are not insurable in the ordinary insurance market, e.g. liability arising out of ionising radiations or contamination by radioactivity from any nuclear fuel.

Using the same numbering as that in the specimen policy in Appendix 1, the following brief comments explains why the exclusions appear and what they mean.

Injury to the categories of persons mentioned is excluded because this risk is usually and more properly insured under an Employers’ Liability policy.
Property belonging to the insured is excluded from a Public Liability policy because such property should be insured under a separate Material Damage policy. For instance, if a contractor has loaned property to a third party and then negligently damages the property while it is still in the custody of the third party, the contractor cannot claim under its own Public Liability policy for damage to its own property.

Third party property in the insured’s charge or control is excluded because insurers take the view that it too should be insured under a Material Damage policy. In practice a great deal of discussion takes place on the wording of this particular exception and amendments are made. However, the exception does make it clear that when a contractor is working in a third party’s premises, those premises and their contents are to be regarded as not being in the contractor’s charge or control for the purposes of activating the exception.

Passenger lifts, aircraft, marine vessels, vehicles and plant are excluded because they should be insured under separate policies.
Traditionally the making good by a contractor of defective site work or materials is regarded by insurers as a trade risk and is therefore excluded: the policy is not intended to be a guarantee as to the skill or competence of the contractor’s employees.
Contractual liability, i.e. liability assumed under agreement, is often an excluded risk under Liability Insurance policies. The reason for this is that while an insurer can generally assess from its own information and experience the risk of injury or damage arising out of tort, it is less easy when liability attaches under contractual agreements. In the United Kingdom, contracting parties are free to contract in whatever terms they wish and liability is frequently transferred from one person to another. A contractor may, therefore, assume very onerous responsibilities which require specific declaration to insure and, if accepted, special underwriting.

This exception is, therefore, often qualified by the words in brackets ‘(other than as defined in Endorsement 1)’ to enable a contractor to negotiate with insurers to include some or all aspects of liability assumed under the construction contract. The point will be explained in greater detail when Endorsement 1 is considered. In some policies the exception does not appear.

The object of the pollution provision is to keep out of cover the potentially very substantial clean-up costs and related liabilities for death or injury caused over a period of years as a result of what are considered by insurers to be trade risks or a lack of care by producers of waste.
This exception appears because it deals with risks which are not insurable in the commercial insurance market.
Like exception 7, exception 8 deals with risks which are not insurable in the commercial insurance market.

Section 5– Endorsements

Endorsement 1

This Endorsement overrides and amends the exception dealing with liability under agreement. Where the contractor has entered into an agreement with a principal, i.e. the Employer under ICE Conditions of Contract, then the policy will protect the contractor in respect of the contractual liability assumed but only so far as concerns injury to third parties or damage to third party property. The policy thus indemnifies a contractor against limited liability under, for example, Clause 22(1) of ICE 6, subject always to the other terms and exceptions of the policy. However, the policy will not pay for the cost of making good defective work or materials, or damage to structures erected by the insured, since these are still excluded perils. Nor will the policy pay for liquidated damages arising from delay. These are not risks covered by the policy in the first place.

Acontractor may enter into other agreements where contractual liability is assumed, e.g. hire of plant. Such liability would not be covered by the above policy since the plant owner is not the principal for whom the contractor has agreed to carry out work.

Endorsement 2

The policy is in the name of the insured – typically in contracts which are subject to ICE Conditions, the Contractor. To comply with ICE Conditions of Contract, which require the insurance also to indemnify the principal (the Employer), Endorsement 2 appears. Thus the policy grants an indemnity to the Employer and complies with, for example, Clause 23(1) of ICE 6.

Section 6– The schedule

The description of ‘the Business’ must be accurate. It must embrace all the activities in which a contractor is engaged. If work is done outside those business activities the contractor is uninsured. For example, in one claim a tunnelling contractor was working near a factory. The factory owner urgently required some equipment in his factory to be cut out and removed. The contractor agreed to do it but caused a fire resulting in substantial damage and was sued. The contractor’s Public Liability policy did not provide protection because the work did not fall within the definition of work normally carried out by tunnelling contractors.

Other amendments that may appear to the policy

The specimen policy in Appendix 1 is meant to be a typically average Public Liability policy. In practice a number of other limitations may apply.

Damage to property

The policy may exclude damage to property arising out of the removal or weakening of support, or alternatively will grant the cover but subject to a low limit of indemnity.

Professional negligence

The policy may exclude what the insurer considers to be a ‘professional negligence’ risk on the basis that this should be insured under a Professional Indemnity policy. Thus the policy may exclude injury or damage arising out of faulty advice, design or specification, or breach of professional duty.

Hazardous work

Certain forms of ‘hazardous’ work may be excluded. This may be on the basis that the insurer does not wish to cover it, or on the basis that the contractor does not wish to pay the additional premium to include it. The policy may, therefore, exclude work in connection with the use of explosives, tunnelling or demolition.

Pure financial loss

It will be remembered that the policy only operates if there is personal injury or damage to property. In those events the policy will provide indemnity against the liability for the injury or damage and the financial loss arising as a result of such injury or damage. What the policy will not do, however, is to provide indemnity where the liability is for pure economic loss.

It is useful to consider what is meant by pure economic loss, the circumstances where it is likely to be insured by the Public Liability policy and the extent to which it needs to be insured having regard to the potential liability of the contractor therefor.

What is pure economic loss? It will certainly include the loss arising in the event of infringement of intellectual property rights such as breach of copyright or patent, and awards in respect of defamation (libel and slander). It will also include losses which arise without physical damage to the tangible property of the person who suffers the loss.

There are essentially three ways in which liability for economic loss might arise:

as a result of a breach of contract;
as a result of negligence; and
as a result of the other torts mentioned in item 3 of Section 2 of the policy.

The policy will cover liability in respect of the last-mentioned type of claim. Unless the policy is extended it will not cover liability for pure economic loss arising as a result of breach of contract or negligence.

Pure economic loss is recoverable as damages for breach of contract provided that it falls within the rule in Hadley v. Baxendale (1854). That which is recoverable is (1) the loss which may fairly and reasonably be regarded as arising naturally, that is to say according to the usual course of things, from the breach, or (2) the loss which ought to have been foreseen, or in the contemplation of the parties, at the time the contract was made.

The position in negligence is more difficult. Except where there is a negligent mis-statement within the meaning of Hedley Byrne v. Heller & Partners (1963), pure economic loss is not recoverable. That which is regarded in law as pure economic loss may be divided into two types.

The first is exemplified by the decision of the House of Lords in D&F Estates Limited v. Church Commissioners (1989). An apartment block had been built by a main contractor for a developer. The plasterwork to the interior of the apartments had been carelessly carried out by a domestic sub-contractor such that the plaster was defective and required replacement. The tenants of the apartments sued the main contractor in negligence for damages representing the cost of removing and replacing the plaster. There was no personal injury or damage to property save for damage to carpets and decor. The claim was held to be for pure economic loss which was not recoverable. The Court went on to say that the principle established by Donoghue v. Stevenson (1932) was that a manufacturer of a product is liable if, due to negligent manufacture, the product causes injury or damage to property, but that damage to the product itself was not included and was recoverable only by one contracting party against another. The principle was applied, by analogy, to buildings. The tenants were unable to recover damages from the main contractor and, on the facts, were unable to recover the damage to carpets and decor because the main contractor was not liable for the errors of the plastering sub-contractor. The main contractor’s only duty in that regard was to employ a competent sub-contractor – which he had done.

The second type of case is where the claimant has nothing to do with the works or the finished product but is affected by the carrying out of the works. A good example of the law relating to recovery of pure economic loss is the case of Spartan Steel & Alloys Limited v. Martin & Co. (Contractors) Limited (1973). The facts, in brief, are that Spartan were aluminium smelters and producers whose plant was run by electricity supplied through cables belonging to the electricity supply authority for the area. Martin damaged the cables so that the power supply to Spartan ’s factory was interrupted. Spartan claimed (i) the value of material which had solidified in the plant and the cost of breaking it out; (ii) loss of profit on that material; and (iii) further loss of profit due to the downtime caused by the lack of electricity. Spartan were entitled to recover (i) and (ii) but not (iii), which was pure economic loss unconnected with damage to Spartan’s property.

When financial loss cover (the insurance term for the only cover available for pure economic loss) is granted as an extension to a Public Liability policy it is subject to many limitations, e.g. it may exclude the cost of repairing or replacing defective work, failure of a product to fulfil its intended function, breach of professional duty, infringement of plans, copyrights, patents, designs and liquidated damages. Moreover, not all insurers are prepared to provide this cover.

An example of a typical financial loss wording is as follows.

‘The company shall subject to the terms and conditions of this Policy indemnify the Insured against:

Liability for accidental Financial Loss occurring during the period of insurance (not occasioned by loss of or damage to Property)

The indemnity granted by this Extension shall not apply in respect of

(a) the first 10% or £xx whichever is the greater of the damages costs or claimant’s expenses which shall be retained by the Insured as his own liability and uninsured
(b) any liability which is assumed by the insured by agreement (other than liability arising out of a condition or warranty implied by law) unless such liability would have attached in the absence of such agreement
(c)any liability arising from a breach of professional duty
(d)passing off or infringement of patent copyright design trademark or trade name
(e)any liability for a breach of obligation owed by the insured as an employer to an Employee
(f)the cost of repairing replacing or recalling any faulty product or material’.

Sub-Contractors

The Insured’s vicarious liability arising out of the use of subcontractors is covered but the policy gives no direct indemnity to the sub-contractors themselves. They are responsible for arranging their own insurance. However, the position is negotiable and where it is necessary for special contracts to meet the requirements of contract conditions, the policy can be extended by negotiation to include an indemnity to the subcontractors themselves.

Policy conditions

Policy conditions have already been considered in principle in Chapter 1. Here the particular conditions in the specimen policy in Appendix 1 are considered.

A requirement that immediate notification is given to insurers of any injury or damage or any claim. The object is to give an insurer the chance to investigate while the evidence is still fresh.
A condition prohibiting an insured from negotiating any claim or repudiating liability or admitting liability. This is on the basis that if the Insurer is going to pay, the Insurer has the right to decide those matters.
Where a claim exceeds the limit of indemnity selected by the Contractor, the Insurer has a right to apply that limit to the Contractor’s claim and thereafter withdraw from the claim. In other words, if the limit of indemnity is £1 million and a claim against the Contractor is for £10 million the Insurer can give the contractor £1 million, pay the costs incurred so far and thereafter leave negotiation of the claim with the Contractor. The insurer then has no further involvement.
A condition that where there is more than one policy in force (as there often is), each policy shall contribute according to a formula; for example, if there are two similar policies, each may pay half of the claim.
A condition requiring the Insured to exercise reasonable care in the conduct of business to prevent injury, loss or damage. The House of Lords has, however, decided (in Sofi v. Prudential Assurance) that before insurers can invoke the condition they have to show that the Insured’s, i.e. the director or senior management’s, conduct was reckless – in other words that the Insured acted with actual knowledge and recognition that a danger existed but not caring whether or not it was averted.
A condition requiring that if the risk changes the Insured must give notice in writing to the Insurer.
A condition giving the Insurer the right to cancel the policy by sending 30 days’ notice by registered letter to the Insured’s last known address.

6 Liability to employees within ICE Conditions of Contract

Previous text has described how ICE Conditions of Contract require a Contractor to indemnify an Employer against claims in respect of death or injury to any person, where ‘any person’ includes third parties and an Employer’s and Contractor’s employees.

However, most ICE Conditions of Contract do not require a Contractor to insure specifically against liability to Contractor’s employees. This is because, in the UK, employee liability insurance is compulsory in law anyway up to a stated minimum amount, by virtue of the Employers’ Liability (Compulsory Insurance) Act 1969. Where ICE Conditions of Contract are to be used outside the UK, any statutory requirements for such insurance should be determined and appropriate cover obtained.

The following paragraphs give details of the requirements of the various ICE Conditions of Contract.

ICE 6, Clause 24

Wording of Clause 24 – Accident or injury to work people

‘The Employer shall not be liable for or in respect of any damages or compensation payable at law in respect or in consequence of any accident or injury to any operative or other person in the employment of the Contractor or any of his sub-contractors save and except to the extent that such accident or injury results from or is contributed to by any act or default of the Employer his agents or servants and the Contractor shall indemnify and keep indemnified the Employer against all such damages and compensation (save and except as aforesaid) and against all claims demands proceedings costs charges and expenses whatsoever in respect thereof or in relation thereto’.

Commentary on Clause 24

Accidents to workmen and other people in the employment of a contractor or a contractor’s sub-contractors are included implicitly in Clause 22 of ICE 6 (i.e. the reference to ‘any person’ in Clause 22(l)(a)). Since Clause 24 is the more specific, liability matters would normally be dealt with under Clause 24.

The Contractor has to indemnify the Employer against all damages and compensation paid by him and legal costs and expenses so incurred unless ‘contributed to by any act of default of the Employer his agents or servants’.

The intention of Clause 24 is to deal with the Contractor’s employees, i.e. persons under a contract of service or apprenticeship. As described earlier, those liabilities are the subject of compulsory Employers’ Liability insurance, with the Contractor in this instance being the Employer concerned. However, the wording of Clause 24 also embraces accident or injury to persons in the employment of any Contractor-appointed sub-contractor. The latter matters would be covered by a Contractor’s Public Liability insurance. The result is that a Contractor looking for insurance protection against the indemnity given under Clause 24 will require cover under both Employers’ and Public Liability policies.

There is no contractual requirement under Clause 24 for a Contractor to insure liability for employees. Employees are also excluded from the requirement to obtain third party insurance in Clause 23(1) (see Chapter 4). One advantage of a contractual requirement (as opposed to only a statutory requirement) is that it would enable an Employer to demand that a Contractor should produce evidence and details of employee liability cover and of continuing payment of premiums. A contractual requirement can be introduced by an additional appropriate contract condition. In this way an Employer can then require evidence of insurance and can determine that the law has been complied with and that there are no restrictions or limitations on the cover, e.g. excluding hazardous works such as tunnelling or demolition where that is appropriate to the Works.

What constitutes an ‘employee’ under the Employers’ Liability (Compulsory Insurance) Act is discussed further in Chapter 7.

ICE Design and Construct,Clause 24

The wording is identical to ICE 6.

ICE Minor Works

There is no specific requirement expressly stated in ICE Minor Works for insurance to cover accidents or injuries to employees. As already described, this is because such insurance is a statutory requirement of all employers and hence is compulsory anyway. However, Clause 10.3 requires insurance against damage, loss or injury for which the Contractor is liable under Clause 10.2 (i.e. ‘to any person or property whatsoever ⋯’ which would include employees.) This non-specific contract requirement for employee insurance thus enables an Employer to require a Contractor to produce the policy and evidence that premiums are being paid, as discussed previously.

NEC, Clause 84 – Insurance cover

Clause 84 in part relates to insurance to cover a Contractor’s liability to employees.

Wording of Clause 84.1

‘The Contractor provides the insurances stated in the Insurance Table except any insurance which the Employer is to provide as stated in the Contract Data. The Contractor provides the additional insurances as stated in the Contract Data’.

Insurance Table

Insurance against | Minimum amount of cover or minimum limit of indemnity
Liability for death of or bodily injury to employees of the Contractor arising out of and in the course of their employment in connection with this contract. | The greater of the amount required by the applicable law and the amount stated in the Contract Data for any one event.

Wording of Clause 84.2

‘The insurances are in the joint names of the Parties and provide cover for events which are at the Contractor’s risk from the starting date until the Defects Certificate has been issued.

Contract Data, Part one – Data provided by the Employer

Paragraph 8 in part relates to Employer requirements for the Contractor’s insurance cover of liability to employees. The relevant part-wording is:

‘The amount of the minimum limit of indemnity for insurance in respect of death of or bodily injury to employees of the Contractor arising out of and in the course of their employment in connection with this contract is ⋯’

Another of the ‘Optional Statements’ enables the Employer to provide insurance against liability to Contractor’s employees instead of the Contractor. It requires the Employer to fill in details of the indemnity to be provided and any applicable deductibles.

Commentary on Clauses 84.1, 84.2 and Paragraph 8 of the Contract Data

The Contractor must provide insurance against liability for injury to, or death of, the Contractor’s employees.

The Employer states the minimum amount of indemnity required per event, but the Table acknowledges that there may also be a statutory limit placed by legislation where the Contractor acts as an employer, e.g. the UK Employers’ Liability (Compulsory Insurance) Act 1969.

There remains an option for an Employer to provide a Contractor’s insurance cover of employees. This could be relevant in territories where there was no statutory obligation for compulsory insurance cover to be obtained by employers.

The joint names policy permits an Employer to rely on the insurance cover where a Contractor’s employee claims against the Employer or both Employer and Contractor, instead of solely the Contractor.

7 A Contractor's Employer's Liability policy

A specimen Employer's Liability policy is included in Appendix 2. It is numbered in sections to make the following text easier to follow. As with all other insurance policies, there is no standard policy and they vary from insurer to insurer. The policy reproduced in Appendix 2 is, however, typical of those in daily use.

An Employer's Liability policy protects a contractor, as an employer, against legal liability for death of, injury to or disease sustained by the contractor's employees in the course of their employment.

Employer's Liability insurance in the United Kingdom is compulsory by virtue of the Employers' Liability (Compulsory Insurance) Act 1969. There are certain exceptions, such as employers who are government bodies. The intention behind compulsory insurance is that if an injured employee has a valid claim for damages against an employer, compulsory insurance will see that the employee obtains compensation regardless of the financial status of the employer.

Unlimited cover

There are certain technical regulations laid down in the Act, but they are not relevant to this chapter. Although the Act stipulates that the minimum limit of indemnity under compulsory Employers' Liability insurance shall be £2 million for any one occurrence, until 1995 insurers continued, in practice, to provide indemnity unlimited in amount. From 1995 the latter position changed and a limit of £10 million per occurrence was imposed by insurers. A higher limit of indemnity is available from some insurers, up to possibly £25 million, depending on the nature of the risk.

The Act provides that a Certificate of Insurance must be issued to prove that the employer is insured, and copies of that Certificate must be displayed at the insured's place of business or, where he has more than one place of business, at each place of business where he employs people.

Who is an employee?

In modern times it has become increasingly difficult to recognise who is an employee so as to create a legal employer/employee relationship.

Doubts can arise in deciding whether a person is engaged under a contract of service so as to be an employee, or under a contract for services so as to be an independent contractor.

Over the years the courts have laid down many tests for deciding whether a person is an employee. It is, therefore, relevant to see who engages the employee, pays wages, determines entitlement to holidays or pays National Insurance contributions, regulates work and has the power of dismissal. In the main, the deciding factor has been the ‘control' test. An employee is subject to the control of an employer as to the manner in which the work is done, since the employer can tell the employee what to do and how to do it. However, in the case of highly skilled employees, the control test is hardly appropriate. It cannot be said, for example, that a skilled surgeon is subject to the control of an employer over the way the surgeon's medical work is carried out. Nor can it be said that other highly skilled people are under the control of their employer. Thus on occasions the ‘integration test' has been used. Was the work done by the employed person integral to the employer's business or merely accessory to it? If it was integral there would be an employer/ employee relationship but this is not necessarily so if it was merely accessory to it. But that test, too, is not perfect. In the construction industry (where there is much use of labour gangs, labour-only contractors and other self-employed individuals), borderline cases often arise. No matter what label is given or used by a person, e.g. ‘self-employed contractor', the courts will look behind the label to ascertain the true relationship.

Section 1 – The opening clause

This is similar to the clause seen in connection with the Public Liability Policy. Again it makes the proposal for insurance the basis of the contract, so that any inaccuracy may invalidate the policy. Again it is important to note that it is only ‘the business' described in the schedule which is covered. A firm described as a building contractor will not necessarily be covered when operating as a civil engineering contractor.

Section 2 – Employees

The cover relates only to employees under a contract of service or apprenticeship with the contractor, i.e. where there is an employer/employee relationship.

As already mentioned, labour gangs and self-employed contractors often fall into a grey area and many policies are endorsed to the effect that such persons and those mentioned in Exclusion 1 to Section 4 of the Public Liability policy shall be deemed to be employees under a contract of service or apprenticeship for the purposes of the policy. Thus the insured's liability for accident or injury to these workers is covered.

The policy relates only to employees who are employed in Great Britain, Northern Ireland, the Isle of Man and the Channel Islands, or temporarily working abroad. Doubts can arise over the word ‘temporary'. In the case of long-term contracts abroad it is necessary to clarify the position with the insurers. Often local legislation may dictate that policies have to be arranged with insurers in the country where the contract is being performed.
The employer is protected only against claims for bodily injury or disease. Property damage is not covered, although in practice, where an employee sustains damage to his clothing and personal effects at the same time as he is injured, such damage is usually paid in addition to compensation for the injuries.
The bodily injury or disease has to be caused during the period of insurance. The word ‘caused' is used deliberately with diseases in mind. Injury consequent upon an accident is usually immediately apparent. There are some diseases, however, such as asbestosis, cancer and noise-induced hearing loss, which may be caused over a long period of time and may not be diagnosed until 20 or 30 years later. Provided the disease was caused during the period of insurance, the policy is operative. An employer must, therefore, be able to trace policies and the insurers for many years back (in some cases 30 years) to ascertain which insurance cover was in place when the disease was caused. The policies, if there are more than one, then share the claim, depending upon how much of the disease was ‘caused' during the periods for which each of the policies was in force – a difficult point to establish. It is sometimes possible to extend a policy to cover claims made during the period of validity of a policy for diseases caused before its inception, but not all insurers are prepared to give this cover. If earlier causation or cover cannot be determined, or no ‘claims made' cover agreed, then a contractor will be liable, without insurers'; support, for the damages attributable to the uninsured period.
The injury or disease must arise out of and in the course of employment with the contractor. Where an employee is injured in out-of-work activities and has a valid claim against an employer, that employer will usually find insurance protection within the Public Liability policy, and not under the Employer's Liability policy.
The bodily injury or disease to be covered must arise in connection with the business described in the policy – hence the importance of having the business correctly described.

Section 3 – The indemnity

Paragraph 1

This states that the insurers will indemnify an employer against liability at law in respect of injury or disease to employees. The expression ‘liability at law' covers all forms of liability, i.e. the policy is not restricted to negligence. The policy is, however, a strictly legal liability policy. It is not a policy which simply makes up the employee's loss of wages while away from work because the employer feels there is a moral obligation to do so.

A stipulation that for employees working abroad a claim must be brought in the courts of the United Kingdom is not always included in policies; if possible, it should be removed since it limits the cover.

Paragraph 2

The policy protects an insured against additional liability imposed by construction contracts with Principals (such as the Employer) and where necessary indemnifies the Principal in the same way as the insured. Thus a Principal (Employer) becomes in effect an insured person under a Contractor's policy. It is necessary to add here that under ICE 6 there is no requirement for a Contractor to insure, or for an Employer to be a named insured under a Contractor's Employer's Liability policy.

Section 4 – Legal costs

In addition to paying the damages resulting from a valid claim by an injured employee, the insurers will also pay the legal costs and expenses incurred in handling and negotiating settlement of the claim.

The final paragraph of Section 4 deals with a technicality which arises from the Employers' Liability (Compulsory Insurance) Act, which was passed to make sure that an injured employee obtained compensation. Prior to the Act, there were circumstances where insurers could refuse to pay under their policy because the insured was in breach of the policy conditions, e.g. by not notifying a claim to the insurers in time. In such circumstances the injured person still had a common law claim for damages against the employer but the employer might not be in a financial position to pay them. The employee, therefore, would not receive compensation.

The Act, therefore, limited the right of an insurer to repudiate liability in certain circumstances. For example, where an insured fails to comply with the conditions requiring prompt notification of a claim to insurers, or failed to take reasonable care to prevent injury to employees, the insurer must pay the injured employee and recover the payment from the insured.

Section 5 – The schedule

This is self-explanatory.

Section 6 – Policy conditions

As explained in Chapter 5, all policies have conditions which must be complied with. A breach of these conditions may give the insurer the legal right to avoid the claim.

Other points

The person indemnified by the policy is the Employer, normally a limited liability company. Most policies, however, indemnify directors, managers and employees as well. Such persons would be at risk for two reasons. First, they have a duty to their employer under their contracts of service to perform their work reasonably and competently so as not to cause loss to the employer. Thus, if by the negligence of one employee a fellow employee is injured, resulting in the employer paying damages, the employer having paid those damages can legally recover them from the negligent employee. If the insurer pays, then under the principle of subrogation the insurer can sue the employee for repayment. In practice there are agreements to the effect that an insurer will not do so.

Secondly, each person, even though an employee, is responsible for his or her own act of negligence. Thus, if one employee negligently injures a fellow employee, there is nothing to stop the negligent employee being sued personally even though the employer would be vicariously liable as well.

By extending the policy to grant an indemnity to directors, managers and employees, in addition to the named insured, such other persons are protected.

Directors who are employed under a contract of service with the insured are regarded as employees in the same way as any other employee. In the case of outside directors who may not be under a contract of service, the policy can be altered to treat these people as though they were directors under a contract of service.
Exclusions in the policy may apply either because a contractor states that a type of work is not undertaken or because the contractor is not prepared to pay the premium to include that type of work. Thus the policy may exclude, for example, an indemnity for employer's liability to employees engaged on demolition, tunnelling or work at certain heights or certain depths in the ground.

8 Care of the Works within ICE Conditions of Contract

Under ICE conditions of contract a Contractor has an obligation to complete and to hand over to an Employer an undamaged project.

ICE 6, Clause 20

The three paragraphs of this Clause apportion responsibility for loss or damage to the Works between the Contractor and the Employer. The following contractual definitions are relevant.

• ‘Permanent Works’ means the permanent works to be constructed and completed in accordance with the contract.
• ‘Temporary Works’ means all temporary works of every kind required in or about the construction and completion of the Works.
• ‘Works’ means the Permanent Works together with the Temporary Works.

Wording of Clause 20(1) — Care of the Works

‘(a) The Contractor shall save as in paragraph (b) hereof and subject to sub-clause (2) of this Clause take full responsibility for the care of the Works and materials plant and equipment for incorporation therein from the Works Commencement Date until the date of issue of a Certificate of Substantial Completion for the whole of the Works when the responsibility for the said care shall pass to the Employer.
(b) If the Engineer issues a Certificate of Substantial Completion for any Section or part of the Permanent Works the Contractor shall cease to be responsible for the care of that Section or part from the date of issue of such Certificate of Substantial Completion when the responsibility for the care of that Section or part shall pass to the Employer.
(c) The Contractor shall take full responsibility for the care of any outstanding work and materials plant and equipment for incorporation therein which he undertakes to finish during the Defects Correction Period until such outstanding work has been completed.’

Commentary on Clause 20(1)

The Contractor is fully responsible for the care of the Works from the Works Commencement Date until the date of issue of a Certificate of Substantial Completion. (This obligation does not prevent a Contractor from seeking contribution from any negligent third party who might be considered actually responsible, for the costs of any loss or damage that the Contractor has had to make good. For example, Clause 4(4) provides that a Contractor remains liable for all sub-contractor’s work.)

The Certificate of Substantial Completion can apply to any Section or part of the Permanent Works. After issue, the care of that Section passes to the Employer. The employer must then make independent arrangements, which might include insurance, to cover those new areas of risk.

However, the Contractor remains responsible for the care of any outstanding work agreed to be undertaken during the Defects Correction Period.

Wording of Clause 20(2) — Excepted Risks

‘The Excepted Risks for which the Contractor is not liable are loss or damage to the extent that it is due to

(a) the use of occupation by the Employer his agents servants or other contractors (not being employed by the Contractor) of any part of the Permanent Works
(b) any fault defect error or omission in the design of the Works (other than a design provided by the Contractor pursuant to his obligations under the Contract)
(c) riot war invasion act of foreign enemies or hostilities (whether war be declared or not)
(d) civil war rebellion revolution insurrection or military or usurped power
(e) ionizing radiations or contamination by radioactivity from any nuclear fuel radioactive toxic explosive or other hazardous properties of any explosive nuclear assembly or nuclear component thereof and
(f) pressure waves caused by aircraft or other aerial devices travelling at sonic or supersonic speeds.’

Commentary on Clause 20(2)

Excepted Risks are common exceptions in insurance policies (except that riot is normally insured under policies issued in England, Scotland and Wales, the Isle of Man and the Channel Isles but not Northern Ireland). The onus of proving that an Excepted Risk operates is upon a Contractor.

The use or occupation of Permanent Works by the Employer or his agents, servants or other contractors, resulting in injury, loss or damage to the Works, is an Excepted Risk.

‘A fault, defect, error or omission in the design of the Works (other than a Contractor’s design)’ is also an Excepted Risk retained by an Employer, who can sue whoever is considered to be responsible. The words ‘fault defect error or omission’ have a wider interpretation than ‘negligent’ design. Thus the exception will apply to a faulty design by anyone (other than a design for which the Contractor is responsible) even if it was not a negligent one.

Wording of Clause 20(3) — Rectification of loss or damage

‘(a) In the event of any loss or damage to

(i) the Works or any Section or part damage thereof or
(ii) materials plant or equipment for incorporation therein

while the Contractor is responsible for the care thereof (except as provided in sub-clause (2) of this Clause) the Contractor shall at his own cost rectify such loss or damage so that the Permanent Works conform in every respect with the provisions of the Contract and the Engineer’s instructions. The contractor shall also be liable for any loss or damage to the Works occasioned by him in the course of any operations carried out by him for the purpose of complying with his obligations under Clauses 49 and 50.

(b) Should any such loss or damage arise from any of the Excepted Risks defined in sub-clause (2) of this Clause the Contractor shall if and to the extent required by the Engineer rectify the loss or damage at the expense of the Employer.
(c) In the event of loss or damage arising from an Excepted Risk and a risk for which the Contractor is responsible under sub-clause (l)(a) of this Clause then the Engineer shall when determining the expense to be borne by the Employer under the Contract apportion the cost of rectification into that part caused by the Excepted Risk and that part which is the responsibility of the Contractor.’

Commentary on Clause 20(3)

Other than damage caused by Excepted Risks, any damage, loss or injury from any cause whatsoever to the Works, while the Contractor is responsible for them, must be put right at the Contractor’s own expense. The intention of the drafters seems to be that ‘any cause whatsoever’ includes any non-excepted negligence on an Employer’s part, and that the Contractor will not be able to sue the Employer where the Employer was at fault. (ICE 6 Insurance Clauses (see Chapter 9) require insurance for the joint benefit of Contractor and Employer so that whoever is responsible will be protected by insurance.)

Where loss or damage arises from any of the Excepted Risks, the Contractor must rectify the loss or damage if required to do so by the Engineer, at the expense of the Employer.

If a Contractor causes damage to the Works during or after the Defects Correction Period (the reference in Clause 20(3) to obligations under Clauses 49 and 50), the Contractor is liable also for that damage.

ICE Design and Construct, Clause 20

The wording is the same as ICE 6 with the following exceptions.

Clause 20(1) — Care of the Works

(a) In sub-clause (a) the superfluous word ‘Works’ is deleted from before the phrase ‘…from the Works Commencement Date …’
(b) In sub-clause (b) the word ‘Engineer’ is replaced by the words ‘Employer’s Representative’. This has no particular insurance implications. Following the final word ‘Employer’ are the additional words ‘Provided also that the Contractor shall remain responsible for any damage to such completed work caused by or as a result of his other activities on site’.

This is a common-sense clarification to recognise the fact that the Contractor would be responsible for damage the Contractor incurs to works that have been handed over to an Employer.

Clause 20(2) — Excepted Risks

(a) In sub-clause (b) the words ‘for which the Contractor is not responsible under the Contract’ replace the parenthetic words ‘(other than a design provided by the Contractor pursuant to his obligations under the Contract)’. In effect these words mean the same, the Design and Construct version being slightly simpler. However, when Clause 20(2)(b) is rewritten without the double negative at present within it, it states that ‘… the Contractor is liable [for] loss and damage to the extent that they are due to any fault defect error or omission in the design of the Works for which the Contractor is responsible under the Contract’.

Clause 20(3) — Rectification of loss or damage

(a) In sub-clause (a) the words ‘and the Engineer’s instructions’ have been deleted after the words ‘… provisions of the Contract’. As a requirement of the Contract is to comply with the Engineer’s instructions, this is a deletion of superfluous words.
(b) In sub-clause (c), the words ‘then the cost of rectification shall be apportioned accordingly’ replace the previous words ‘then the Engineer shall, when determining the expense to be borne by the Employer under the Contract, apportion the cost of rectification into that part caused by the Excepted Risk and that part which is the Responsibility of the Contractor’. Again the substitution is a simplification of the existing words with no particular insurance implications.

ICE Minor Works, Clause 3.2

Wording of Clause 3.2 — Care of the Works

‘(1) The Contractor shall take full responsibility for the care of the Works from the starting date until 14 days after the Engineer issues a Certificate of Practical Completion for the whole of the Works pursuant to Clause 4.5.
(2) If the Engineer issues a Certificate of Practical Completion in respect of any part of the Works before completion of the whole of the Works the Contractor shall cease to be responsible for care of that part of the Works 14 days thereafter and the responsibility for its care shall then pass to the Employer.
(3) The Contractor shall take full responsibility for the care of any outstanding work which he has undertaken to finish during the Defects Correction Period until such outstanding work is complete.’

Commentary on Clause 3.2

It will be seen that the main provisions are similar to ICE 6 except that ICE Minor Works requires a Contractor to care for the works for 14 days longer. This means that any Contractor’s works insurance will also be required for 14 days longer, with the Employer having a correspondingly increased time within which to arrange his own cover.

NEC, Clause 81 — The Contractor’s risks

Wording of Clause 81.1

‘From thestarting date until the Defects Certificate has been issued the risks which are not carried by theEmployer are carried by the Contractor. ’

NEC, Clause 82 — Repairs

Wording of Clause 82.1

‘Until the Defects Certificate has been issued and unless otherwise instructed by the Project Manager the Contractor promptly replaces loss of and repairs damage to the works, Plant and Materials.’

NEC, Clause 80 — Employer’s risks

Part-wording of Clause 80.1

‘The Employer’s risk are

— Loss of or damage to Plant and Materials supplied to theContractor by the Employer, or by Others on the Employer’s behalf, until theContractor has received and accepted them.
— Loss of or damage to the works, Plant and Materials due to

— war, civil war, rebellion, revolution, insurrection, military or usurped power,
— strikes, riots and civil commotion not confined to the Contractor’s employees,
— radioactive contamination.

— Loss of or damage to the parts of the works taken over by the Employer except loss or damage occurring before the issue of the Defects Certificate which is due to

— a Defect which existed at take over,
— an event occurring before take over which was not itself an Employer’s risk or
— the activities of the Contractor on the Site after take over

— Loss of or damage to theworks and any Equipment, Plant and Materials retained on Site by the Employer after a termination except loss and damage due to the activities of the Contractor on the Site after termination.
— Additional Employer’s risks stated in the Contract Data’.

Commentary on Clauses 80.1, 81.1 and 82.1

In the context of these Clauses, ‘Plant and Materials’ are those items incorporated into the Works, whereas ‘Equipment’ is equipment used by the Contractor and not incorporated into the Works.

There are several critical dates relating to the care of the Works, Plant and Materials, and Equipment. These are the ‘starting date’, the date(s) when plant and materials supplied by the Employer (or on the Employer’s behalf) are received and accepted by the Contractor, the taking-over date, and the issue date for the Defects Certificate.

The Employer remains responsible for loss or damage to Plant and Materials supplied by the Employer until the contractor receives and accepts them.

The Employer is always responsible for loss or damage due to war, strikes, radioactive contamination etc., no matter at what time during the contract they occur.

The Employer becomes responsible for loss or damage after taking over the works, except for certain matters which arose before the issue of the Defects Certificate.

The Employer generally becomes responsible for loss or damage to the works and any Employer-retained Equipment, Plant and Materials on site after a contract termination.

The Employer can agree to accept responsibility for additional risks by stating them in the Contract Data.

Risks that are not the Employer’s rest with the Contractor. The Contractor is responsible for promptly replacing loss or repairing damage to the Works, Plant and Materials until the Defects Certificate is issued, unless otherwise advised by the Project Manager. This includes matters which are at the Employer’s risk.

9 Requirement for Works insurance within ICE Conditions of Contract

The ICE Conditions of Contract state whether or not a Contractor is required to insure his/her responsibilities for loss or damage to contract works. In the event of serious loss or damage, where insurance exists both a Contractor and an Employer then know that a sum of money should be available from an insurance policy which will enable the Contractor to repair or make good such loss or damage. In the absence of insurance, a Contractor may not financially be in a position to carry out the repairs, resulting in delays which cause problems for both the Contractor and the Employer.

A Contractor will obtain cover for loss of or damage to the Works within a CAR policy, the nature of which was outlined in Chapter 1and which is dealt with in more detail in Chapter 10.For works which involve the erection of plant with construction of buildings, the equivalent is an EAR (Erection All Risks) insurance policy. It will be recognised that some contracts (such as power stations or petrochemical installations) may therefore be insured by either CAR or EAR policies when they have significant plant or civil engineering elements respectively. In this text, EAR policies are not mentioned further.

Cover under a CAR Policy is not provided for uninsurable risks, or matter which could be the foreseeable consequence of the way a Contractor proceeds with undertaking Works (i.e. an insurer will not underwrite purely commercial risks taken by a Contractor), or for Employer's risks (whether defined formally as ‘Excepted’ risks or otherwise). The policy will normally continue in force until the Works or completed portions are handed over to an Employer, and for damage caused to Works by the presence of a Contractor during a maintenance/defects correction period.

The insurance requirements of the various ICE Conditions of Contract are described below.

ICE 6, Clause 21

Wording of Clause 21(1) — Insurance of Works, etc.

‘The Contractor shall without limiting his or the Employer’s obligation and responsibilities under Clause 20 insure in the joint names of the Contractor and the Employer the Works together with materials plant and equipment for incorporation therein to the full replacement cost plus an additional 10% to cover any additional costs that may arise incidental to the rectification of any loss or damage including professional fees cost of demolition and removal of debris.’

Commentary on Clause 21(1)

The fact that a Contractor is obliged to arrange insurance does not detract from ‘his obligations and responsibilities for the care of the Works under Clause 20’.

As already noted, insurance in ‘joint names’ is a co-insurance of the Employer and the Contractor.

‘The Works together with materials plant equipment for incorporation therein’ must be insured ‘for the full replacement cost plus an additional 10% to cover any additional costs that may arise incidental to the rectification of any loss or damage including professional fees cost of demolition and removal of debris’. In calculating the full replacement cost, it would be incorrect simply to insure for the contract value. Suppose the Contractor is carrying out a contract worth £10 million, that the contract is expected to last for three years, but that the whole Works are completely destroyed by fire shortly before handover. Allowing for inevitable delays, such as for removing debris, it may be some time before the Contractor can start reconstruction. Certainly it is unlikely that the three-year contract could be completed at the original figure of £10 million. What the insured parties require is a sum of money to enable the Contractor to rebuild the damaged works, bearing in mind the increased cost. Thus, in calculating the sum insured, a Contractor has to estimate the future increased cost of rebuilding. Although some Contract Works insurance policies have a small inflation factor built into them, a prudent Contractor should always make sure that the sum insured represents the true cost of rebuilding (plus the 10% required by the Clause).

In cases where a total loss is an unreasonable expectation, then it should be made permissible under a contract for a Contractor to insure not on a ‘full value’ basis but on what is known as a ‘first loss’ basis (subject to the wording of Clause 21 being altered to permit this). In other words, the Contractor calculates what the maximum loss is likely to be and insures for that figure (plus 10%). This situation may occur when the Works are to be built in sections over a wide area and it is not possible to visualise total loss of all the sections at the same time from the same cause.

Insurance is not contractually required under Clause 21 for Contractor’s Equipment (including temporary buildings) which will not be part of the Permanent Works. A Contractor may insure such items as part of the CAR policy but separate policies for Equipment are also available.

Wording of Clause 21(2) — Extent of cover

‘(a) The insurance required under sub-clause (1) of this Clause shall cover the Employer and the Contractor against all loss or damage from whatsoever cause arising other than the Excepted Risks defined in Clause 20(2) from the Works Commencement Date until the date of issue of the relevant Certificate of Substantial Completion.
(b) The insurance shall extend to cover any loss or damage arising during the Defects Correction Period from a cause occurring prior to the issue of any Certificate of Substantial Completion and any loss or damage occasioned by the Contractor in the course of any operation carried out by him for the purpose of complying with his obligations under Clauses 49 and 50.
(c) Nothing in this Clause shall render the Contractor liable to insure against the necessity for the repair or reconstruction of any work constructed with materials or workmanship not in accordance with the requirements of the Contract unless the Bill of Quantities shall provide a special item for this insurance.
(d) Any amounts not insured or not recovered from insurers whether as excesses carried under the policy or otherwise shall be borne by the Contractor or the Employer in accordance with their respective responsibilities under Clause 20.’

Commentary on Clause 21(2)

The cover must be ‘against all loss or damage from whatever cause arising other than the Excepted Risks’.

The insurance must be in force ‘from the Works Commencement Date until the date of issue of the relevant Certificate of Substantial Completion’.

Insurance must also cover ‘loss or damage ⋯ during the Defects Correction Period ⋯ occasioned by the Contractor ⋯ for the purpose of complying with his obligations under Clauses 49 and 50’.

Under Clause 21(2)(c), a Contractor is not obliged ‘to insure ⋯ against ⋯ repair or reconstruction of any work constructed with materials or workmanship not in accordance with the requirements of the Contract unless the Bill of Quantities shall provide a special item for this insurance’. This means that insurance is not required against the cost of making good faulty or defective workmanship or materials. Insurers take this to be part of a Contractor’s trade risks and not, generally speaking, insurable as part of a normal Contractor’s Works policy. Uninsured losses for which a Contractor is responsible under Clause 20, including policy deductibles and excess over limits of indemnity, must still be borne by the Contractor.

ICE Design and Construct, Clause 21

The only notable difference in wording between Clause 21 of ICE Design and Construct and Clause 21 of ICE 6 occurs in sub-clause 21(2)(c). The final phrase of the latter states that insurance is not required for defective workmanship or materials ‘unless the Bill of Quantities shall provide a special item for this ‘insurance’, whereas ICE Design and Construct uses the words ‘unless the Contract otherwise requires’. ICE Design and Construct is thus apparently less limited than ICE 6 in that it recognises that Employer requirements for such insurance can be stated in sections of contract documents other than Bills of Quantities, e.g. in the Conditions of Contract. An insurance requirement for defective work cover, if it exists, is therefore no different between the two forms, but a Contractor may need to look more widely afield in the contract documents in order to determine whether it exists. However, although there is little difference in the wording of Clause 21, the amendment to Clause 20(2) means that the insurance must include damage caused by the Contractor’s design.

ICE Minor Works,Clause 10.1

Wording of Clause 10.1 — Insurance of the Works

‘(1) If so stated in the Appendix the Contractor shall maintain insurance in the joint names of the Employer and the Contractor in respect of the Works (including for the purpose of Clause 10 any unfixed materials or other things delivered to the Site for incorporation therein) to their full value against all loss or damage from whatever cause arising (other than the Excepted Risks) for which he is responsible under the terms of the Contract.
(2) Such insurance shall be effected in such a manner that the Employer and the Contractor are covered for the period stipulated in Clause 3.2 and are also covered for loss or damage arising during the Defects Correction Period from such cause occurring prior to the commencement of the Defects Correction Period and for any loss or damage occasioned by the Contractor in the course of any operation carried out by him for the purpose of complying with his obligations under Clauses 4.7 and 5.2.
(3) The Contractor shall not be liable to insure against the necessity for the repair or reconstruction of any work constructed with materials or workmanship not in accordance with the requirements of the Contract.
(4) Any amounts not insured or not recovered from insurers whether as excesses carried under the policy or otherwise shall be borne by the Contractor or the Employer in accordance with their respective responsibilities under Clauses 3.2 and 3.3.’

Commentary on Clause 10.1

Insurance to cover damage to the Works is not compulsory. This reflects the fact that minor works contractors will usually rely solely upon the cover provided by their annual all-risks policies. Nevertheless, an Employer has the option of requiring a Contractor to take out works insurance, by making an appropriate amendment to the Appendix to the Conditions of Contract. However, it might prove administratively easier to handle, cheaper overall, more likely to provide comprehensive cover and less likely to result in disputes as to who is liable, if an Employer takes out specific project insurance in the Employer’s name covering the activities of the Contractor. An Employer might also exercise the latter option to avoid asking several minor works contractors on the same project to take out separate insurances.

NEC,Clause 84 — Insurance cover

Clause 84 in part relates to insurance of the Works by a Contractor.

Wording of Clause 84.1

‘The Contractor provides the insurances stated in the Insurance Table except any insurance which the Employer is to provide as stated in the Contract Data. The Contractor provides additional insurances as stated in the Contract Data. ’

Insurance Table

Insurance against | Minimum amount of cover or minimum limit of indemnity
Loss of or damage to the works, Plant and Materials. | The replacement cost, including the amount stated in the Contract Data for the replacement of any Plant and Materials provided by the Employer.
Loss of or damage to Equipment. | The replacement cost.

Wording of Clause 84.2

‘The insurances are in the joint names of the Parties and provide cover for events which are at the Contractor's risk from the starting date until the Defects Certificate has been issued.’

Contract Data, Part one — Data provided by the Employer

One of the ‘Optional Statements’ is entitled ‘If the Employer is to provide Plant and Materials’.

The wording of the Optional Statement is as follows.

‘The insurance against loss of or damage to the works, Plant and Materials is to include for Plant and Materials provided by the Employer for an amount of ’

Another of the ‘Optional Statements’ enables the Employer to provide insurance of the Works, Plant, Materials or Equipment instead of the Contractor. It requires the Employer to fill in details of the indemnity to be provided and the applicable deductibles.

Commentary on Clauses 84.1 and 84.2

The insurances under these Clauses are to cover Contractor’s risks.

A Contractor must insure against loss of or damage to the Works, Plant and Materials (i.e. those items included in the Works) at replacement cost: this includes any replacement cost stated in the Contract Data by the Employer for Plant and Materials supplied by the Employer.

A Contractor must also insure for a replacement cost to cover loss of or damage to Equipment (i.e. Contractor's equipment used but not incorporated in the Works).

A Contractor must supply any additional insurance stated by the Employer in the Contract Data.

Alternatively the Employer must insure the Works, Plant and Materials, and/or Equipment if he so states in the Contract data.

The insurances must be in the joint names of the Employer and Contractor (i.e. as co-insureds) and extend from the starting date until the date of issue of the Defects Certificate.

10 A Contract Works policy

Contract Works policies vary from insurer to insurer; a typical example is reproduced in Appendix 3. The policy is written on the basis of ‘all risks of loss or damage’. This is a misleading form of shorthand used in the insurance industry and does not mean that every loss or damage is covered by the policy: it does no more than describe the insuring wording in Section 1, which is subject to policy exceptions, terms and conditions.

Section 1 — Damage to the Works

This sets out the circumstances in which damage to the Works is covered.

The Insured must have paid or have agreed to pay the premium.
The insurer will indemnify the Insured against loss or damage to the Works by repair, reinstatement or replacement.
To comply with the requirements of the construction contract the Insured will be the Contractor and the Employer.
The indemnity relates to all forms of loss or damage (although a number of exceptions, to be discussed later, limit the cover). Arguments can arise as to whether insurers require the Works to be physically damaged and the meaning of ‘damage’. For example, if a hole is dug and the sides collapse, or it is flooded, is the hole damaged?
The property insured is described in detail in a schedule to the policy.
The loss or damage must occur during the currency of the policy. It follows that once the policy lapses there is no cover.
The loss or damage must occur on sites within Great Britain, Ireland, Northern Ireland, the Isle of Man or the Channel Islands, although in practice the policy can be extended to apply to damage in other parts of the world.
The policy is limited to loss or damage on or adjacent to the contract site but a number of extensions can widen this cover, as will be explained in the following section. The Contractor is responsible for loss or damage to goods and materials off the site and while in transit, but the policy can be extended to give this cover. The Contractor may also have a responsibility to insure goods and materials, the ownership of which may have been vested in the Employer under the pertaining construction contract conditions, before delivery to the site.

Section 2 — Extensions

Transit — loss or damage to the Works or materials while in transit — is covered, other than for transport by sea or air (because of the much heavier risks involved). Loss or damage to any mechanically propelled vehicle operating under its own power is not covered because the Contractor should have this risk insured under separate plant or motor policies.

Employees’ tools and effects are excluded because to include these would result in many small claims which would erode unreasonably the premium paid to the insurer.

By including the Principal (Employer) as an insured party under the contract, the policy complies with any Construction Contract conditions requiring the Contractor to insure the works in the joint names of the Employer and the Contractor.
Extension 3, dealing with Architects’, Surveyors’ and Consulting Engineers’ fees, is self-explanatory. The Insurer will not pay the fees incurred in assisting the Insured to prepare a claim against the Insurers since they see no logic in financing claims against themselves.
Many expensive claims are paid under the extension covering the removal of debris. It is not only the cost of removing debris from the site which is covered but also the cost of removing it to another dumping ground, which may be some distance away. Property remaining on the contract site may have to be shored or propped up.
Materials and goods, while not on the site of the contract but intended for inclusion in the Works and for which the Contractor is responsible, are covered by an extension to the policy while they are stored off-site. Under some standard conditions of contract the ownership of certain goods and materials stored elsewhere but intended for the site is transferred to the Employer. However, the Contractor remains responsible for any loss or damage to them and must, under the conditions of contract, insure them under against damage from ‘any cause’. In fact, notwithstanding any contract requirement, a policy will not cover damage from ‘any cause’: it has limitations and exclusions.

Section 3 — Exceptions

Exceptions 1 to 13 deal with injury, loss or damage in circumstances where the Insurer is not prepared to pay.

The Insured’s retained liability, e.g. deductibles or excesses, normally appear in policies of this type. They are intended to cut out small claims, and are imposed by insurers where they wish to reduce the effect of an adverse feature of the risk, or to make Contractor take more care.
The object of the policy is to cover the risks of loss or damage to the works during the construction period. Once a contract has been completed and the works have been handed over to the Employer, the risk passes to the Employer, who has responsibility to arrange insurance. Care is necessary to ensure that there is no shortfall in cover during the changeover period of risk from Contractor to Employer.
Once the construction period has finished, the policy ceases to apply except to pick up any liability for loss or damage under insurance contract terms applicable to any Maintenance Period or Defects Liability Period. Once a Certificate of Completion, or equivalent, has been issued, at the end of such period, the remaining risk of loss or damage passes to the Employer.

Works ‘taken into use by the owner, tenant or occupier’ are excluded. The exclusion may be modified to permit use or occupation, provided all the facts are disclosed to the Insurer and the appropriate premium is paid.

There are six items contained in this exception.

(a) Damage to any existing structure is not covered because it is not part of the Contract Works. Borderline cases may arise: then there is nothing to stop an agreement being reached with the insurers to regard such existing property as part of the Contract Works for the purposes of the policy and to have the sum insured and, if appropriate, the premium increased accordingly. Thus damage to existing property will be covered on an ‘all risks’ basis, regardless of fault.

Normally, however, the position is that if a Contractor damages existing property while carrying out the Works, and this is caused by the Contractor’s negligence or where the Contractor is liable under a Construction Contract condition, the Employer can sue the Contractor, who should be able to recover under a Public Liability policy.

(b) Deeds, bonds, bills of exchange etc. are excluded because these risks should be separately insured under a Money policy; in any case it is doubtful whether the items could be considered to be part of the Permanent or Temporary Works.
(c) This item removes the mechanical vehicle risk from the policy because the Contractor should have these risks insured under a separate Motor or Plant policy. If an item of plant is used solely as a tool of trade on-site, then the policy applies.
(d) Despite the fact that Construction Contract conditions may require it to be insured, damage to Contractor’s constructional plant due to its own breakdown is excluded because this should be covered by a Machinery Breakdown insurance. Such insurance is expensive and, since constructional plant may be subject to rapid deterioration and damage unless subject to regular maintenance, it is not available unless the Insurer can be satisfied as to the Contractor’s maintenance arrangements.
(e) Vessels or craft made to float in or on water are excluded because these can be insured more adequately by Marine insurance.
(f) This exception, dealing with property for which the Contractor is relieved of responsibility by Construction Contract conditions, is important. Thus, even though an Employer is insured as a named party under the policy, the Employer will have no protection in respect of loss or damage arising from Excepted Risks. Many of these are not insurable by the commercial insurance market. However, damage arising out of use or occupation by the Employer, his agents or servants or other contractors, is a risk which the Insurer may be prepared to include in the policy if full details are made available. The same may be true of loss or damage arising from fault, defect, error or omission in the design of the Works, a subject which will be mentioned in greater detail later. Unless consideration is given to providing an Employer with some measure of cover for these Excepted Risks at the time the insurance is arranged, the Employer remains uninsured unless independent arrangements are made elsewhere.

The exception contains five alternative Defect Exclusion (DE) clauses which are known as DE1 to DE5. These were published by the Association of British Insurers and adopted in 1995 by most of the insurers issuing CAR policies in the UK. They are provisions regarded as acceptable for use in CAR policies. A brief description of their effect is given below.

DE1 — Outright Defect Exclusion

Insurers will not pay for loss or damage caused by specified defects; such matters are regarded as trade risks. It will be remembered that there must first be an instance of loss or damage before the policy operates at all; it is therefore unnecessary to exclude the cost of repairing defects.

DE2 — Extended Defective Condition Exclusion

The exclusion is limited to that which is defective and the property relying for support or stability on the defective Works. Other Works which are not defective, but are damaged, are insured. An example is a steel-framed building with the steel members bolted together, surrounded by a dwarf wall. A bolt securing roof members is defective so that the building collapses and destroys the dwarf wall. DE2 would exclude the entire steel frame (as relying for support on the defective bolt) but would leave the dwarf wall within cover.

DE3 — Limited Defective Condition Exclusion

This is similar to DE2 but there is no exclusion in respect of works which rely upon defective Works for support or stability. Applying DE3 to the previous example would remove from cover the roof section of the building (which is defective) but would leave the other damage within cover.

DE4 — Defective Part Exclusion

Here the exclusion is limited to only the defective part or component and not the Works of which it is a part. In the foregoing example DE4 would be effective to remove only the defective bolt from cover.

DE5 — Design Improvement Exclusion

The cover is much wider: in the event of damage, the policy will pay for repairs. Only the cost of improvement is uninsured. In the example the entire loss would be insured except for improvements such as an upgrade in the bolt specification for increased strength.

The extent to which an insurer will be prepared to insure on the basis of DE4 or DE5 is uncertain. While it is a matter of negotiation in each particular case, it is unlikely that contractors other than the major UK civil engineering companies, with a proven track record, will be able to insure on those terms.

Whether there is a ‘defect’ should be decided first and independently of any question of fault, or negligence on the part of the designer. In Hitchens Hatfield v. Prudential (1993) the court decided that while the phrase ‘defectively designed’ in a policy exclusion required proof of fault, the phrase ‘defective in design’ did not. The question is simply: ‘Is there a defect?’ If that question is answered in the affirmative, the exclusion will apply.

The cost of normal upkeep or normal making good.
Damage by wear, tear, rust and mildew is excluded because insurers again regard it as a trade risk that is not insurable. The exclusion is usually qualified to make it clear that other parts of the Works which are free from such defects, but are damaged as a result of them, are covered.
Loss or damage to property only discovered when an inventory is made is excluded, because insurers only intend to pay for loss or damage which can be traced to an identifiable cause or event. They can then investigate that event to see whether it is within the terms of the policy. To identify a loss only by an inventory does not define the causative event and prevents the Insurer from applying policy terms and conditions such as policy excess and, in particular, whether more than one excess applies.
Delay, non-completion or consequential loss or damage of any kind is excluded because the object of the policy is to cover physical loss or damage to the Works, not loss consequent upon delay. Losses incurred by the Employer, e.g. loss of income or profit because of late completion following damage, may be covered under a separate policy, usually called ‘Advance loss of profits’ (ALOP) policy. A Contractor may also be able to insure against some of the consequences of delay, e.g. liquidated damages, under a separatge policy but not in the CAR insurance market.
—13. The remaining exceptions 10, 11, 12 and 13 deal with exclusions which are found in all insurance policies and relate to risks against which there is no commercial insurance available.

Other exceptions

Because insurance policies are not standardised there may be additional exceptions which appear in addition to those shown in the specimen policy in Appendix 3. For example, other policies may exclude loss or damage arising out of cessation of work arising, for instance, where there is a strike or labour dispute or a problem with suppliers or delays in deliveries; as a consequence a site may be left unattended or with a minimum of security. This would represent an increase in risk, which is why the exception would appear. Another example is where a contract includes the installation or erection of plant or machinery which has to be tested or commissioned before the Employer will accept it. Testing and commissioning may be excluded on the basis that such activities represent high risks, particularly those relating to breakdown, fire or explosion. The risks may be included subject to special negotiation with insurers.

Section 4 — Limits of liability

The sums insured on the Works, Plant and other property are set out in the typical policy schedule in Section 7.

The final paragraph of Section 4 allows the sum insured to be reinstated, should there be a claim. Thus if property is insured for £2 million and there is a claim for £1 million, the sum insured is not reduced. It automatically reverts to £2 million. An additional premium is payable.

Section 5 — General conditions

Like all insurance policies there are conditions which have to be complied with before an insured is entitled to the benefit of the policy.

This is a standard condition in mjost policies and is self-explanatory.

Take care

An Insured is required to take all reasonable precautions to prevent loss or damage, since insurance is not intended to be a substitute for good management and supervision. The theory is that the Insured should proceed in exactly the same way whether or not he is insured. Insurance is not an excuse for taking short cuts — although in practice, of course, this happens.

Should a Contractor fail to take reasonable precautions to prevent loss or damage, however, he runs the risk of breaching the terms of the policy. The Insurer would, however, have to prove recklessness on the part of a director or senior manager to establish a breach of the condition in the same way as in respect of the similar condition in the Public Liability policy.

Change in risk

This condition requires any change in the nature of the risk to be notified to the insurers, and the Insured in the meantime must take such additional precautions as are necessary. It represents an onerous condition and the Insured must be careful to remember it and comply with it. It is there because the premium and risk assessment are calculated on the facts known to the Insurer. If the risk changes, the Insurer needs to know. It may affect the premium, the assessment of the risk and how much of the risk the Insurer decides to carry. Insurers often reinsure parts of their risk to keep their own exposure within reasonable boundaries.

Observing terms of policy

This is again a typical condition which makes the original proposal for insurance the basis for the insurance contract, so that if anything is wrong or inaccurate in the proposal the policy is voidable.

The condition makes observance of policy terms and conditions a condition precedent, so that the insured has to comply with the terms and conditions of the policy before there is entitlement to indemnity.

Premium adjustment

This condition is a typical clause dealing with the adjustment of premium. Most premiums are calculated by applying a rate per cent to contract values at the beginning of the year and at the end of the year the insured declares the correct values when they are known. An adjustment of premium is then made and the insured is either entitled to a return of premium or charged an additional premium.

Section 6 — Claims conditions

These conditions should be read carefully by an Insured. For example, in the event of some event occurring which may give rise to a claim, the Insurer has to be informed in writing with full details. This is to enable investigation of the occurrence while the facts are still fresh in the minds of all the people concerned.

Notification of the police is necessary in the case of theft, loss or wilful damage. If loss or damage due to these causes is not notified to the insurers within three calendar months, there is no cover under the policy.

Condition 5 allows arbitration if there is a dispute as to the amount to be paid under the policy. It does not arise where there is a dispute relating to the words of the policy itself. Historically, Contractors have preferred to have disputes about wording dealt with by the courts. Insurers, therefore, have restricted their insurance contract arbitration clauses to matters of quantum only.

All the terms and conditions of a policy should be understood and complied with. In practice the terms and conditions of the policy are frequently breached by an Insured, but insurers nevertheless will normally deal reasonably with most claims.

Section 7 — The schedule

This is largely self-explanatory, but some points require special attention.

The Insured will normally be shown as the Contractor (particularly if reliance is placed on an annual policy which has to cover more than one contract). To comply with the ICE Conditions of Contract an Employer obtains indemnity under the heading ‘Indemnity to Principals’ discussed earlier, which for practical reasons insurers regard as tantamount to insurance in the joint names.

Where a single policy is being issued to cover the Works (rather than relying on a Contractor’s annual policy), then the Insured would be shown as the Contractor, the Employer and other interested parties such as sub-contractors and financiers.

The period of insurance must cover the full period of the contract. Where the Contractor is relying on an annual policy, it must be renewed each year.

The business should be correctly described to cover all the activities, a point which has been mentioned several times previously.

The description of the Contract Works insured is self-explanatory and includes free-issue materials. It is important for the Contractor to ensure that the sums insured are correct and are sufficient to provide enough money to replace any work lost or damaged. To select the tender price is dangerous, as variations to the contract plus inflation during the period of the contract may make this figure inadequate. As the contract moves towards completion there is a build-up of risk; what is required is a sum of money to enable the Contractor to recomplete the contract, should there be a total loss. This could include demolition and debris removal as well as rebuilding. The policy does provide for some inflation by stipulating that the sum insured should not exceed 120% of the estimated original tendered contract price, including the value of free materials.

11 vidence of insurances, failure to insure and other clauses within ICE Conditions of Contract

Where there is a contractual requirement to insure, and particularly where a ‘joint names’ policy has been arranged under which a second party may directly benefit, either party should be able to check the extent of the cover and also to make sure that the policy contains no limitations or exclusions which leave that party unacceptably unprotected.

For Contractor-arranged insurance, for example, a Contractor should be required to produce to an Employer evidence of insurance and payment of premium. Where a Contractor has more than one policy, e.g. a policy covering, say, the first £5 million of the risk and further policies ‘topping up’ this limit to a higher figure, say £20million, all policies should be mentioned. It must be noted that project-specific policies take some time to prepare and may only be available some months after Works have commenced. Reliance may have to be placed initially on summary information from brokers. Evidence of annual policies should be more readily and more quickly available. Parties should call for and examine policies for two main reasons. First, any indemnity given by one Party to another against claims for injury or damage is worthless unless the first Party has the resources to back up the indemnity: if that Party is inadequately insured, alternative financial resources to do this may be lacking. Secondly, since a second Party is treated as an insured person under a joint policy, that Party has the right, if he so wishes, to claim on the policy for indemnity in the event of loss or damage. The second Party thus needs to be assured as to the adequacy of cover.

The following sections describe the requirements of the various ICE Conditions of Contract.

ICE 6, Clause 25

Wording of Clause 25(1)— Evidence and terms of insurance

‘The Contractor shall provide satisfactory evidence to the Employer prior to the Commencement Date that the insurances required under the Contract have been effected and shall if so required produce the insurance policies for inspection. The terms of all such insurances shall be subject to the approval of the Employer (which approval shall not unreasonably be withheld). The Contractor shall upon request produce to the Employer receipts for the payment of current insurance premiums.’

Commentary on Clause 25(1)

A Contractor has to arrange joint name insurances against loss or damage to the Works (i.e. the Temporary and Permanent Works but excluding Contractor’s Equipment (see Clause 21) and for third party public liability (see Clause 23)). In both cases Clause 25(1) requires the terms of the policies to be approved by the Employer. When required to do so by the Employer, the Contractor must produce the policies prior to the Commencement Date, and receipts showing payment of the premiums.

Wording of Clause 25(2)— Excesses

‘Any excesses on the policies insurance effected under Clauses 21 and 23 shall be as stated by the Contractor in the Appendix to the Form of Tender.’

Commentary on Clause 25(2)

An excess is an amount an insured must pay before drawing on an insurer’s indemnity. As a general rule the higher the excess, the cheaper the premium. An Employer will therefore want to know how much cover is provided by insurance and how much risk is being retained directly by the Contractor. An excess is therefore one of the terms which is subject to the approval of an Employer in accordance with Clause 25(1).

Wording of Clause 25(3)— Remedy on Contractor’s failure to insure

‘If the Contractor fails upon request to produce to the Employer satisfactory evidence that there is in force any of the insurances required under the Contract then the Employer may effect and keep in force any such insurance and pay such premium or premiums as may be necessary for that purpose and from timeto time deduct the amount so paid from any monies due to which may become due to the Contractor or recover the same as a debt due from the Contractor.’

Commentary on Clause 25(3)

Clause 25(3) says that if a Contractor shall fail on request to produce to an Employer ‘satisfactory evidence’ that contractually required insurances are in force, the Employer may take out such insurances and deduct the premiums from amounts due to the Contractor. The Clause refers to ‘satisfactory evidence’ that the insurances are in force. The best evidence is the policies themselves or certified copies of them. That is the only way an Employer can fully know the terms and conditions. The Contractor or his insurers or brokers will usually initially only be able to produce certificates or letters to the effect that certaininsurances are in force and for what period. These certificates or letters are never satisfactory by themselves since they usually include qualifications such as that the insurance is ‘subject otherwise to the terms exceptions limitations and conditions of the policy’. This is of little use to an Employer since it is those terms, exceptions, limits and conditions which may severely limit the cover and to which he would have objected, had he known them. (However, if the certificates or letters stated that an insurance complied with the Contractor’s obligations— without making such a qualification— this could be untrue. Those issuing the certificates or letters would then be exposed to claims for damages for negligent mis-statement if an Employer who placed reliance upon them sustained a loss because the insurances were inadequate.)

Should the Contractor fail to produce ‘satisfactory evidence’ of insurance, there are practical problems for an Employer attempting to arrange equivalent joint names insurances himself,as allowed by Clause 25. Before insurers issue policies, they require much information to enable them to assess the risk and the premium. This would include, for example, details of how long a Contractor has been in business, his experience of the type of work involved, previous insurances held by him and any claims paid under those policies for the preceding five years, and how much they cost. Such knowledge may not be available to the Employer who would, therefore, have difficulty himself in effecting the joint names insurances required. However, the Employer can arrange insurances in his own name protecting his own interest in the works and covering his own legal liability risk, and can charge that premium to the Contractor.

Similarly, should an excess proposed by a Contractor prove unacceptable to an Employer as one of the ‘terms’ of a policy according to Clause 25(1), the Employer can obtain extra cover for that excess and charge the Contractor for that cover under Clause 25(3).

Wording of Clause 25(4)— Compliance with policy conditions

‘Both the Employer and the Contractor shall comply with all conditions laid down in the insurance policies. In the event that the Contractor or the Employer fails to comply with any condition imposed by the insurance policies effected pursuant to the Contract each shall indemnify the other against all losses and claims arising from such failure.’

Commentary on Clause 25(4)

This Clause means that should either party not fulfil the requirements of a policy (e.g. by not giving proper and timely notification of a claim) leading to a loss being incurred because of non-payment by insurers, the non-performing party must accept the financial consequences applicable to the other party.

ICE Design and Construct,Clause 25

Although there are very minor changes in wording, Clause 25 of ICE Design and Construct is essentially the same as that of ICE 6.

ICE Minor Works,Clauses 10.6 and 10.7

Wording of Clause 10.6— Employer to approve insurance

‘⋯ insurance shall be effected with an insurer and in terms approved by the Employer (which approval shall not be unreasonably withheld) for at least the amount stated in the Appendix.’

Wording of Clause 10.7— Contractor to produce policies of insurance

‘Both the Employer and the Contractor shall comply with the terms of any policy issued in connection with the Contract and shall whenever required produce to the Employer the policy or policies of insurance and the receipts for the payments of the current premiums.’

Commentary on Clauses 10.6 and 10.7

The following points will be noted in comparison with ICE 6.

There is no specific requirement to produce satisfactory evidence of insurance prior to a commencement date.
There is no requirement for a Contractor to state insurance excesses. There is, however, a requirement that terms are subject to approval by the Employer. If an Employer is unhappy with the excess indicated by scrutiny of insurance terms and conditions, he can withhold approval.
There is no clause covering a failure of a Contractor to comply with the terms of any policy or even to insure. However, such failure would be a breach of contract (as would a failure to obtain insurance satisfactory to the Employer, including level of excess). An Employer paying for cover himself would be entitled in litigation to recover as damages any costs incurred as a result of that breach.

NEC, Clause 85 — Insurance policies

Wording of Clause 85.1

‘The Contractor submits policies and certificates for the insurance which he is to provide to the Project Manager for acceptance before the starting date and afterwards as the Project Manager instructs. A reason for not accepting the policies and certificates is that they do not comply with this contract.’

Wording of Clause 85.2

‘Insurance policies include a waiver by the insurers of their subrogation rights against directors and other employees of every insured except where there is fraud.’

Wording of Clause 85.3

‘The Parties comply with the terms and conditions of the insurance policies.’

Wording of Clause 85.4

‘Any amount not recovered from an insurer is borne by the mployer for events which are at his risk and by the Contractor for events which are at his risk.’

NEC, Clause 86— If the Contractor does not insure

Wording of Clause 86.1

‘The Employer may insure a risk which this contract requires the Contractor to insure if the Contractor does not submit a required policy or certificate. The cost of this insurance to the Employer is paid by the Contractor.’

NEC, Clause 87— Insurance by the Employer

Wording of Clause 87.1

‘The Project Manager submits policies and certificates for insurances provided by the Employer to the Contractor for acceptance before the starting date and afterwards as the Contractor instructs. The Contractor accepts the policies and certificates if they comply with this contract. ’

Wording of Clause 87.2

‘The Contractor’s acceptance of an insurance policy or certifiicate provided by the Employer does not change the responsibility of the Employer to provide the insurances stated in the Contract Data.’

Wording of Clause 87.3

‘The Contractor may insure a risk which this contract requires the Employer to insure if the Employer does not submit a required policy or certificate.The cost of this insurance to the Contractor is paid by the Employer.’

Commentary on Clauses 85.1 to 87.3

The intentions of the wording of these clauses appear straightforward.

The Contractor and Employer both have to produce policies and certificates of the insurances required by their respective contractual obligations, before the starting date and periodically thereafter as requested. The Contractor’s insurances are submitted to the Project Manager; the Employer’s insurances are submitted to the Contractor.

If the insurances comply with the contract they are acceptable. Each party must comply with the terms and conditions of their policies.

If either party’s contractually required policy or certificate is not produced when stated by the contract, the other party may insure the risks involved and charge the defaulting party for the costs involved.

12. Sub-Contractors and Sub-Contract agreements

As discussed previously, in claims for personal injury or damage to property the Contractor gives an indemnity to the Employer under the Construction Contract conditions. The Contractor is obliged also to indemnify the Employer in respect of injury or damage which arises from the Sub-Contractor's activities. The FCEC Sub-Contract is intended for use in conjunction with ICE 6, the FCEC D&C Sub-Contract is for use in conjunction with ICE Design and Contruct, and the NEC Subcontract is appropriate for the New Engineering Contract system. The subcontract forms provide that the Sub-Contractor shall indemnify the Contractor against certain kinds of injury, loss or damage and require insurance by the Sub-Contractor.

It will be noted that the term ‘Sub-Contractor’ is used in FCEC Sub-Contract and FCEC D&C Sub-Contract and the term ‘Subcontractor’ in NEC Subcontract. There are other similar differences. Commentary has attempted to follow the appropriate terminology in each case.

FCEC Sub-Contract Clauses 12 and 14

Wording of Clause 12 — Indemnities

‘(1) The Sub-Contractor shall at all times indemnify the Contractor against all liabilities to other persons (including the servants and agents of the Contractor or Sub-Contractor) for bodily injury, damage to property or other loss which may arise out of or in consequence of the execution, completion or maintenance of the Sub-Contract Works and against all costs, charges and expensesthat may beoccasioned to the Contractor by the claims of such persons.

Provided always that the Contractor shall not be entitled to the benefit of this indemnity in respect of any liability or claim if he is entitled by the terms of the Main Contract to be indemnified in respect thereof by the Employer.

Provided further that the Sub-Contractor shall not be bound to indemnify the Contractor against any such liability or claim ifthe injury, damage or loss in question was caused solely by the wrongful acts or omissions of the Contractor, his servants or agents.

(2) The Contractor shall indemnify the Sub-Contractor against all liability and claims against which the Employer by the terms of the Main Contract undertakes to indemnify the Contractor and to the like extent, but no further.’

Commentary on Clause 12

The indemnity applies in respect of injury, damage or loss which arises ‘out of or in consequence of the execution, completion or maintenance of the Sub-Contract Works … ’. In the practical sense that will include all incidents on or about the site of the Sub-Contract Works and where Sub-Contract Work is undertaken off-site. It is no answer to a claim for indemnity by the Contractor to say thatthe injury arises out of employee negligence and not out of or in consequence of the execution of the Sub-Contract Works.

The Contractor is not entitled to the Sub-Contractor’s indemnity if the Contractor is already entitled to a similar indemnity from the Employer under the Main Contract and, under Clause 12(2), passes on to the Sub-Contractor the benefit of that indemnity.

The Sub-Contractor is not bound to indemnify the Contractor where injury or damage is caused ‘solely’ by the wrongful act or omission of the Contractor, his servants or agents. The use of the word solely means that the Contractor must be 100% at fault. Where there is 90% of fault on theContractor and 10% on the Sub-Contractor, the Sub-Contractor still has to indemnify the Contractor for the full amount.

The Sub-Contractor should arrange Employers’ Liability and Public Liability insurances which will also provide indemnity against the liability assumed under Clause 12.

Wording of Clause 14(1) — Liability insurance

‘The Sub-Contractor shall effect insurance against such risks as are specified in Part I of the Fifth Schedule hereto and in such sums and for the benefit of such persons as are specified therein and unless the said Fifth Schedule otherwise provides, shall maintain such insurance from the time that the Sub-Contractor first enters upon the Site for the purpose of executing the Sub-Contract Works until he has finally performed his obligations under Clause 13 (Outstanding Work and Defects).’

Commentary on Clause 14(1)

The ‘Notes for the guidance of Contractors on the completion of the schedules’ at the back of FCEC Sub-Contract say no more than that Part I of the fifth schedule ‘should specify insurances to be effected by the Sub-Contractor’. Having regard to the provisions of Clause 14(2), however, it is suggested that Part 1 of the fifth schedule should refer to Employers’ Liability, Public Liability and Motor insurance for the Sub-Contractor’s own benefit and, if the Sub-Contractor is not to have the benefit of the Contractor’s policy, insurance of the Sub-Contract Works, constructional plant, temporary works, materials and other objects belonging to the Sub-Contractor.

Wording of Clause 14(2) — Insurance of the Sub-Contract Works

‘The Contractor shall maintain in force until such time as the Main Works have been substantially completed or ceased to be at his risk under the Main Contract, the policy of insurance specified in Part II of the Fifth Schedule hereto. In the event of the Sub-Contract Works, or any Sub-Contractor’s Equipment, Temporary Works, materials or other things belonging to the Sub-Contractor being destroyed or damaged during such period in such circumstances that a claim is established in respect thereof under the said policy, then the Sub-Contractor shall be paid the amount of such claim, or the amount of his loss, whichever is the less, and shall apply such sum in replacing or repairing that which was destroyed or damaged. Save as aforesaid the Sub-Contract Works shall be at the risk of the SubContractor until the Main Works have been substantially completed under the Main Contract, or if the Main Works are to be completed by sections, until the last of the sections in which the Sub-Contract Works are comprised has been substantially completed, and the SubContractor shall make good all loss of or damage occurring to the Sub-Contract Works prior thereto at his own expense.’

Commentary on Clause 14(2)

The Guidance Notes published as part of FCEC Sub-Contract say of Part II of the fifth schedule:

‘Part 2 should specify the policy of insurance which the Contractor is effecting in pursuance of Clause 21 of the Main Contract Conditions, if it is intended that the Sub-Contractor shall have the benefit thereof. In such cases his interest should be noted either generally or specifically on the policy and this Part of the schedule should so state. If the Sub-Contractor is not to have any benefit under the policy of the Contractor, then that Part should be marked ‘not applicable’.

With respect to the author of the Guidance Note, where Clause 14(2) applies and the Copntractor insures the Works, the better course would be for the Sub-Contractor to be named in the policy as an insured. The noting of an interest on a policy is no more than an acknowledgement by the Insurer of notice of an interest adverse to that of the named Insured. If the Sub-Contractor is not a named Insured he cannot claim on the policy other than through the Contractor, has no rights against the Insurers and may have no right to receive payment of any policy monies other than through the Contractor.

If the Contractor does insure, the Sub-Contractor should ensure that the Contractor’s policy provides adequate cover in respect of the Sub-Contract Works. The Sub-Contract Works are at the risk of the Sub-Contractor, save to the extent that they are insured by the Contractor’s policy, until substantial completion of the Main Works — which may be some time after the completion of the Sub-Contract Works and after the SubContractor has left the site. Any shortfall in the Contractor’s insurance cover will, therefore, be to the disadvantage of the Sub-Contractor.

FCEC D&C Sub-Contract

The provisions of Clauses 12 and 14 are identical to those in FCEC Sub-Contract. The ‘Notes for the guidance of Contractors on the completion of the schedules’ at the back of FCEC D&C Sub-Contract say of the fifth schedule:

‘Reference should be made to Clause 14 (Insurances) of the SubContract. In completing the two parts of this Schedule the parties shouldtake care to ensure that all insurances required by the Main Contract are effected by one or other of them and that there is no unnecessary duplication of insurance.

Part I should specify insurances to be effected by the SubContractor. Any Professional Indemnity insurance requirements should be stated.’

The mention of Professional Indemnity insurance arises because the Main Contract and the Sub-Contract will have a design element in respect of the permanent works whereas ICE 6 and FCEC Sub-Contract will not. The terms of this guidance note are thought preferable to that which appearsin FCEC Sub-Contract.

NEC Subcontract, Clause 80 — The Employer’s and Contractor’s risks

Wording of Clause 80.1

‘80.1 The Employer’s and Contractor’s risk are

⋆Claims, proceedings, compensation and costs payable which are due to

⋆use or occupation of the Site by the works or for the purpose of the works which is the unavoidable result of the works,
⋆negligence, breach of statutory duty or interference with any legal right by the Employer or the Contractor or by any person employed by or contracted to them except the Subcontractor or
⋆a fault of the Employer or Contractor or a fault in their designs.

⋆Loss of or damage to Plant and Materials supplied to the Subcontractor by the Employer or Contractor or by Others on the Employer’s or Contractor’s behalf, until the Subcontractor has received and accepted them.
⋆Loss of or damage to the works, Plant and Materials due to

⋆war, civil war, rebellion, revolution, insurrection, military or usurped power,
⋆strikes, riots and civil commotion not confined to the Subcontractor’s employees,
⋆radioactive contamination.

⋆Loss of or damage to parts of the subcontract works taken over by the Employer or Contractor, except loss or damage occurring before the issue of the Defects Certificate which is due to

⋆Defect which existed at take over,
⋆an event occurring before take over which was not itself an Employer’s or Contractor’s risk or
⋆the activities of the Subcontractor on the Site after take over.

⋆Loss of or damage to the subcontract works and any Equipment, Plant and Materials retained on Site by the Employer or Contractor after a termination, except loss or damage due to the activities of the Subcontractor on the Site after the termination.
⋆Additional Employer’s or Contractor’s risks stated in the Subcontract Data’.

NEC Subcontract, Clause 81 — The Subcontractor’s risks

Wording of Clause 81.1

‘81.1 From the subcontract starting date until the Defects Certificate has been issued the risks which are not carried by the Employer or the Contractor are carried by the Subcontractor. ’

NEC Subcontract,Clause 82 — Repairs

Wording of Clause 82.1

‘82.1 Unless the Defects Certificate has been issued and unless otherwise instructed by the Contractor the Subcontractor promptly replaces loss of and repairs damage to the subcontract works, Plant and Materials.’

NEC Subcontract, Clause 83 — Indemnity

Wording of Clauses 83.1 to 83.3

‘83.1 Each Party indemnifies the other against claims, proceedings, compensation and costs due to an event which is at his risk. The Contractor indemnifies the Subcontractor against all claims and liabilities against which the Employer indemnifies the Contractor under the main contract.

83.2 The liability of the Subcontractor to indemnify the Contractor is reduced if events at the Employer’s or Contractor’s risk contributed to the claims, proceedings, compensation and costs. The reduction is in proportion to the extent that events which were at the Employer’s or Contractor’s risk contributed, taking into account the responsibilities of each Party under this subcontract.

83.3 The liability of the Contractor to indemnify the Subcontractor is reduced if events at the Subcontractor’s risk contributed to the claims, proceedings, compensation and costs. The reduction is in proportion to the extent that events which were at the Subcontractor’s risk contributed, taking into account the responsibilities of each Party under this subcontract.’

NEC Subcontract,Clause 84 — Insurance cover

Wording of Clauses 84.1 and 84.2

‘84.1 The Subcontractor provides the insurances stated in the Insurance Table except any insurance which the Employer or the Contractor is to provide as stated in the Subcontract Data. The Contractor provides additional insurances as stated in the Subcontract Data.

Insurance Table

Insurance against | Minimum amount of cover or minimum limit of indemnity
Loss of or damage to the subcontract works, Plant and Materials. | The replacement cost, including the amount stated in the Subcontract Data for the replacement of any Plant and Materials provided by the Employer or Contractor.
Loss of or damage to Equipment. | The replacement cost.
Liability for loss of or damage to property (except the subcontract works, Plant and Materials and Equipment and liability for bodily injury to or death of a person (not an employee of the Subcontractor) caused by activity in connection with this subcontract. | The amount stated in the Subcontract Data for any one event with cross liability so that the insurance applies to the parties separately.
Liability for death of or bodily injury to employees of the Subcontractor arising out of and in the course of their employment in connection with this subcontract. | The greater of the amount required by the applicable law and the amount stated in the Subcontract Data for any one event.

84.2 The insurances are in the joint names of the Parties and provide cover for events which are at the Subcontractor’s risk from the subcontract starting date until the Defects Certificate has been issued.’

NEC Subcontract,Clause 85 — Insurance policies

Wording of Clauses 85.1 to 85.4

‘85.1 The Subcontractor submits policies and certificates for the insurance which he is to provide to the Contractor for acceptance before the subcontract starting date and afterwards as the Contractor instructs. A reason for not accepting the policies and certificates is that they do not comply with this subcontract.

84.2 Insurance policies include a waiver by the insurers of their subrogation rights against directors and other employees of every insured except where there is fraud.

84.3 The Parties comply with the terms and conditions of the insurance policies.

84.4 Any amount not recovered from an insurer is borne by the Employer or Contractor for events which are at their risk, and by the Subcontractor for events which are at his risk. ’

NEC Subcontract, Clause 86 — If the Subcontractor does not insure

Wording of Clause 86.1

‘86.1 The Contractor may insure the risk which this subcontract requires the Subcontractor to insure if the Subcontractor does not submit a required policy or certificate. The cost of this insurance to the Contractor is paid by the Subcontractor. ’

NEC Subcontract, Clause 87 — Insurance by the Employer or the Contractor

Wording of Clauses 87.1 to 87.3

‘87.1 The Contractor submits policies and certificates for insurances provided by the Employer or the Contractor to the Subcontractor for acceptance before the subcontract starting date and afterwards as the Subcontractor instructs. The Subcontractor accepts thepolicies and certificates if they comply with this subcontract.

87.2 The Subcontractor’s acceptance of an insurance policy or certificate provided by the Employer or Contractor does not change the responsibility of the Employer or Contractor to provide the insurances stated in the Subcontract Data.

87.3 The Subcontractor may insure a risk which this contract requires the Employer or Contractor to insure if the Contractor does not submit a required policy or certificate. The cost of this insurance to the Subcontractor is paid by the Contractor. ’

Commentary on Clauses 80 to 87

Clauses 80 to 87 are ‘Core Clauses’ and there are other options in the NEC Subcontract which are not considered in this text.

The Core Clauses are straightforward: the risks are apportioned between the parties by Clauses 80 and 81. Repairs to the Works, liability for personal injury and damage to property are then dealt with in Clauses 82 and 83 on the basis of that risk apportionment. Clauses 84 and 85 then set out the required minimum insurance cover.

13 Performance bonds

Performance bonds

A party to a construction contract can partially protect itself from the consequences of premature termination of that contract (perhaps because of solvency or severe financial difficulties) or some other failure to perform contractual obligations by the other party to the contract, by requiring the latter to provide a performance bond. Occasionally, and more often overseas, a Contractor can require a bond from an Employer; it is also possible for a strongly positioned specialist Sub-Contractor to require a bond from a main Contractor. However, in construction contracts, by far the most usual performance bond is one required by an Employer of a main Contractor. The bond is commonly for 10% of a contract value, but the reason for this percentage (compared with any other) is unclear.

Many construction conditions of contract, including ICE 6 and ICE Design and Construct, incorporate suggested Forms of Bond. An Employer has an option, often exercised, to require a Contractor to provide such a bond. The third party bond provider, usually a banker or insurance company acting as what is known as a Surety, will either provide a bond using the standard contract form of words or, if permitted by the Employer, may provide a bond using his own terminology. The Surety binds himself with the Contractor for a stated period of time to pay losses up to an agreed amount sustained by an Employer if the Contractor does not perform his obligations under the contract.

A bond therefore involves three parties, a Surety, a Contractor and an Employer. A bond should be drafted so that it remains in force until the obligations of the Contractor have been completed. In fact most bonds stipulate a date upon which they cease, usually the date of the anticipated end of a maintenance period.

Categories of bonds

There are two basic categories of performance bond. There are ‘on-demand’ bonds, which – at their simplest without conditions attached – may be called upon by an Employer even when sometimes there may not be a reasonable cause. For instance, a ‘falling out’ between an Employer and a Contractor, particularly on overseas contracts, might lead to an unjustifiable call on an on-demand bond. In other words, an on-demand bond, if it is unconditional, can be cashed in at any time the Employer wishes, without the Contractor being in default of his/her obligations under the contract. A Contractor has to pay high premiums for such bonds. On-demands bonds are clearly very onerous and are usually only agreed to with reluctance if required for strong commercial reasons, e.g. if agreement to have such bonds is essential in order to be awarded a contract.

The other category of performance bond is an ‘on-default’ bond, which can be called upon when a Contractor demonstrably fails to undertake obligations under a contract, i.e. the Contractor ‘defaults’.

Both bonds are thus undertakings given by a Surety to make payment to an Employer (or otherwise ensure performance) where a Contractor fails to meet an Employer’s expectations or contractual requirements. They are therefore forms of guarantee which are evidenced in writing. Although a Contractor pays the bond premium, the Employer is ultimately paying for it as it will be reflected in the Contractor’s price for the contract. Employers should bear this in mind when deciding on which type (‘on-demand’ or ‘on-default’) they require.

It should be noted that a Contractor cannot escape the financial consequences of default by providing a bond, since a Surety has common law rights of recovery against the Contractor. These are usually reinforced by the Surety requiring a written form of counter-indemnity or other security from the Contractor, or the Contractor’s parent company.

Duty of Employer to disclose information

A Surety may be released from his obligations if there is a dishonest failure by an Employer to disclose material information which would affect the Surety’s decision of whether or not to provide a bond. Since bonds are not contracts of insurance, there is no general duty on the Employer to disclose all material information as would be the case under an insurance policy. However, a bond may be invalid if it is obtained by Employer fraud or dishonesty concealing material facts relating to risks known to the Employer but which the Surety would not reasonably be expected to know existed. An example would be that the Employer knew that the tender price was far too low in comparison with other tenders because of some mistake by the Contractor.

Sub-Contractors

A main Contractor is responsible for completing the Works and even if the Contractor is prevented from doing so because of poor performance by a Sub-Contractor, a bond will remain valid. A main Contractor may therefore consider demanding bonds from significant Sub-Contractors.

Issuers of bonds

Bonds are usually issued by banks or insurance companies. There are advantages and disadvantages attaching to both.

Banks regard bonds as an extension of their line of credit to a Contractor. They usually know a Contractor better than an insurance company and can therefore issue bonds speedily. However, when issued by a bank, the bond may affect the availability of that bank’s credit to that Contractor, perhaps prejudicing the advance of money in the future to purchase plant and materials, or on other projects taking place during the same risk period. Banks usually pay out on bonds more promptly, as they are less willing than an insurance company to argue or investigate the merits of any claim.

An insurance company will usually issue a bond only after it has made careful enquiries into a Contractor’s financial stability and ability to perform a Contract. The performance of these enquiries is reassuring to an Employer since it indicates that if an insurance company has issued a bond it is satisfied with the risk. Conversely if an insurance company refuses to issue a bond and an Employer is aware of that situation, the Employer might question whether the right Contractor has been selected.

A bond is typically for 10% of the Contract Price, higher or lower amounts may be requested, or no bond may be required at all. An Employer has to decide what percentage is sufficient.

Other forms of bond

There are several other forms of bond.

A bid (or tender) bond is intended to reassure an Employer that a bid is a responsible one and that if the bid is accepted the tenderer will proceed to execute a contract. If the tenderer fails to do so, and an Employer incurs loss and expense in the retendering process, those losses could form a claim under the bond.
Advanced-payment, progress or repayment bonds protect an Employer against any advanced monies being lost through default by the Contractor.
Retention bonds are bonds issued in lieu of retention monies. They can be used to permit the early release of the retention element of monthly progress payments.
Maintenance bonds protect an Employer as an alternative to retention monies during a maintenance period. They provide reassurance that a Contractor will carry out residual obligations during the maintenance period of a Contract.

ICE 6 – Form of Bond

The Form of Bond given in ICE 6 is shown in Appendix 4. The Contractor and Surety are ‘held and firmly bound’ to the Employer. This is joint and several liability and the Employer may sue one or both of the parties for the full amount of the loss.

The bond recognises that the Contractor has agreed with the Employer to enter into a Contract for the construction, completion and maintenance of the Works. If the Contractor duly performs and observes the terms of the Contract the bond is null and void. If the Contractor defaults on the Contract and the Surety satisfies the Employer’s loss, the bond is again null and void. But if the Contractor continues not to fulfil contractual obligations, the balance of the bond will remain available to the Employer until the Contractor does fulfil them.

The bond also provides that ‘no alteration in the terms of the said Contract made by agreement between the Employer and the Contractor or in the extent or nature of the Works to be constructed and completed thereunder and no allowance of time by the Employer or the Engineer under the said Contract nor any forbearance or forgiveness in or in respect of any matter or thing concerning the said Contract . . . shall in any way release the Surety from any liability under the . . . Bond.’ Without this requirement the common law position, i.e. that changes in the risk covered release the Surety, would apply.

As the ICE 6 bond is not meant to be an ‘on-demand’ bond, an Employer has to prove a loss before a Surety pays.

ICE Design and Construct

The Form of Bond is set out in slightly clearer terms in part compared with the bond in the ICE 6. However, there is no significant difference in effect between the two versions.

ICE Minor Works

There is no Form of Bond included within ICE Minor Works. It is presumably considered that other existing provisions, such as payment in arrears for work done and retentions, provide sufficient security. (Indeed, there is a view that perhaps there is sufficient practical Employer risk protection within most types of contract anyway, without the need for additional premium to be paid to Sureties. Employers could increase retentions if not wholly convinced. The provision of bonds certainly appears to be a practice that needs review by Employers to determine what protection is really necessary, considering that it is the Employer who ultimately pays the additional premium bill.)

NEC

There is provision for a performance bond in Clause Gl.l of NEC. Clause Gl.l is given in ‘Secondary Option’ Clause G.

Wording of Clause Gl.l

‘TheContractor gives the Employer a performance bond, provided by a bank or insurer which the Project Manager has accepted, for the amount stated in the Contract Data and in the form set out in the Works Information. A reason for not accepting the bank or insurer is that its commercial position is not strong enough to carry the bond. If the bond was not given by the Contract Date, it is given to the Employer within four weeks of the Contract Date.’

Within the Contract Data, Part one, ‘Data provided by the Employer’ is an Optional Statement, headed ‘If Option G is used’. The Employer must state the value of the performance bond required.

Commentary on Secondary Option Clause G

The provision of a performance bond is optional. If an Employer decides to have one it must be in the form set out in the Works Information (defined in Clause 11.2(5) of NEC), and to the amount defined in the Option Statement. This Clause leaves the decision to require an ICE 6 type of bond, or any other, open to the Employer.

The bond is to be provided to the Employer within four weeks of the Contract Date, otherwise the Contractor is in breach of contract.

A potential problem arises in practice as to how to assess and then to refuse to accept a Surety on the basis that ‘its commercial position is not strong enough’. The purpose of this sentence is clear, and it could be particularly relevant to overseas suretyproviding organisations whose credentials may be unknown. However, should a Project Manager refuse to accept a Surety which turns out to be sound, this would appear to leave the Project Manager open to legal proceedings. If the Project Manager refuses for other reasons, this issue would become an NEC ‘compensation event’ under Clause 60.1(a).

Developments, 1993 to 1995

For many years most standard construction Forms of Bond, including those of the ICE, were worded in a similar manner. All parties had a perceived understanding of what was intended by those words and that they were dealing with ‘on-default’ bonds. However, in 1993 and 1994 several legal cases arose where decisions and commentaries were both critical of standard wording and threw into doubt previous perceived understanding, particularly of what constituted sufficient ‘default’ to enable bonds to be drawn upon.

It was finally left to the House of Lords in 1995 to confirm that Forms of Bond such as those of the ICE were, in effect, default bonds which required a proven breach of contract and incurred damages, against which Sureties could set-off valid counterclaim costs. One problem with this is that there can be considerable delays before a Surety needs to pay out, and that negates one of the objectives of a bond, i.e. to provide an injured party with the finances to proceed as soon as possible.

The courts in 1994 were strongly critical of the confusing and ‘archaic’ forms of words used in typical construction bonds. As a result Sureties, such as those who are members of the Association of British Insurers (ABI), discussed the use of different and specific forms of wording. The intention was that the wording would clarify that, where intended, bonds will definitely be understood to be ‘on-default’ not ‘on-demand’, and that net losses must be proved after taking into account other monies owed under a contract. In parallel the Conditions of Contract Standing Joint Committee (CCSJC) of the ICE, the Association of Consulting Engineers and the Federation of Civil Engineering Contractors also considered the wording for a new ICE Form of Bond which was intended to be comprehensive, to enable prompt payment to be made where there is a clear entitlement, to state the expiratory date and to reflect definitions of terms used in corresponding main contracts so as to avoid misinterpretation and confusion. At the time of writing, a new ICE Form of Bond has yet to be published.

14 The basis of legal liability for breach of professional duty

Liability in contract

Traditionally, the liability of the professional person has been to the client under the terms of the contract for the professional’s services.One of the implied terms of such a contract is that the professional person will exercise reasonable care and skill. Sometimes the contract may contain a specific provisoas, for example:

‘The Consulting Engineer shall exercise all reasonable skill care and diligence in the discharge of the duties to be performed under this Contract ⋯’

Where there is no specific requirement to this effect the courts will imply it into the contract.

Standard of care

The standard of care expected from professional persons was laid down over 100 years ago in Lanphier v. Phipos (1838), where the judge said:

‘Every person who enters into a learned profession undertakes to bring to the exercise of it a reasonable degree of care and skill. He does not undertake if he is an attorney that at all events you shall gain your case. Nor does a surgeon undertake that he will perform a cure, nor does he undertake to usethe highest possible degree of skill. There may be persons who have higher education and greater advantage than he has but he undertakes to bring a fair reasonable and competent degree of skill.’

In Greaves &Co. v. Baynham Meikle (1975), involving a claim against a consulting engineer, the judge said:

‘The law does not usually imply a warranty that [a professional man] will achieve the desired result but only a term that he will use reasonable care and skill. The surgeon does not warrant that he will cure the patient. Nor does the solicitor warrant that he will win the case.’

To decide whether or not a person has exercised reasonable care and skill, the standards expected of the profession as a whole at the time are used as a yardstick. Would other professionals have acted in the same way? If the answer is in the affirmative, then there has been no fall below the required standard. In other words, a professional person is not expected to be perfect and error-free, but is expected to achieve the standards of an average professional undertaking similar work.

Warranties or guarantees

The liability of the professional person will be governed by the terms of the professional services contract with the professional’s client and it is a question of reading that contract as a whole. The contract may require the professional person to warrant or guarantee his professional skill or work. In that case, liability may arise under the terms of the warranty or guarantee, regardless of negligence. It represents an increased risk.

Liability to third parties

Until 1963 the liability of the professional person was to his client, since it was to the client that the duty of care was owed and it was the client who paid for the services. The House of Lords in Hedley Byrne v. Heller & Partners (1963) extended liability to third parties who were not in a contractual relationship with the professional person. The House of Lords held that:

‘If in the ordinary course of business or professional affairs a person seeks information or advice from another who is not under contractual or fiduciary obligation to give the information or advice, in circumstances in which a reasonable man so asked would know that he was being trusted or that his skill or judgement was being relied upon and the person asked chooses to give the information or advice without so clearly qualifying his answer as to show that he does not accept responsibility, then the person replying accepts a legal duty to exercise such care as the circumstances require in making his reply and for a failure to exercise that care an action for negligence will lie if damage results. ’

Owing to that decision the professional person now owes a duty of care in tort to third parties who are placing reliance upon the professional’s skill, advice or judgement. Thus in preparing plans or reports, or issuing certificates in circumstances where a third party other than the client may place reliance upon them, a duty of care will arise.

In cases involving personal injuries to third parties or damage to their property (as distinct from claims for economic or financial loss without injury or damage) the professional person has always owed a duty of care to others not to behave negligently. Thus negligence, e.g. bad design of a structure causing it to collapse on passers-by, will render the professional person liable to the injured persons.

At one time the liability of the professional person to a client was solely contractual. Now the liability is both contractual and tortious. The matter is important because different limitation periods run in contract and tort. Generally a person has six years in which to bring a claim for breach of contract starting from the date of the breach. In claims in tort it is generally six years from the date of the damage (or in cases of personal injury, three years from the date of the injury). Thus the limitation period runs for a longer time in tort cases.

The Latent Damage Act 1986 deals with cases of latent defects, i.e. damage that is hidden and cannot be discovered, such as faulty foundations, and provides that the six-year period should be extended by allowing a claimant a further three years in which to bring his claim from the date the claimant discovered, or ought reasonably to have discovered, the defect. This extension is subject to a long-stop which would bar claims brought more than 15 years from the defendant’s breach of duty.

Limit of liability

It may be possible for a professional person to exclude or limit liability to a client under the terms of the professional services contract between them. The clauses would, however, be subject to the Unfair Contract Terms Act 1977 and would have to be fair and reasonable in the opinion of the courts. It is not possible to contract out of liability for death or personal injuries.

While complete exclusions of liability are unlikely to be considered fair or reasonable, limitations on liability may be. There is no reason why professionals should not attempt, by contractual provision, to limit liability to a stipulated sum, e.g.£100 000 or a multiple of the fee. Professional firms commonly limit their contractual liability to the extent of cover they have under their Professional Indemnity policies. To be effective, such limitations of liability must be brought to the attention of the client before the contract is agreed, so that the client is aware of them and understands them. Such limitation or exclusion clauses are ineffective against third parties since such third parties are not parties to the professional services contract.

ply a warranty that

Contractor’s design and construction contracts

The preceding comments relate to professional firms engaged under contracts to provide professional services. The liability of a contractor agreeing to design and construct a building is different, as a client is then entitled to a structure which is free from defect and fit for its purpose. Thus in the event of designfaults appearing in the structure or its not being able to carry its required loading, it is no defence for the contractor to show that there was no negligence. Instead the contractor must comply with contractual obligations. There is thus an essential difference between design functions undertaken by a contractor and those taken by an independent design consultant. However, where a contractor engages a design consultant to undertake a contractor’s design, the contractor will often try to impose a fitness for purpose obligation within the professional services contract between the contractor and the consultant. The design consultant should resist that liability if it is outside the consultant’s Professional Indemnity insurance cover.

15 Professional Indemnity policies

There is no absolute requirement under ICE Conditions of Contract for Professional Indemnity insurance. However, for completeness of this text and to cover situations where such insurance is made obligatory by special additional conditions of contract, consideration of how professional negligence risks can be covered by insurance is discussed in this chapter.

Typical provisions within Professional Indemnity policies for consulting engineers

As with all insurance policies, Professional Indemnity policies can differ. Typical provisions are given in Appendix 5. Wording may provide:

‘To indemnify the Insured against any claim for damages for breach of professional duty which may be made against them during the period of insurance due to any negligent act error or omission whenever or wherever the same was or was alleged to have been committed by the Insured or their predecessors in business or any employee of the Insured or their predecessors in business in the conduct of the business.’

The following points should be noted.

A claim must be for a breach of professional duty. For example, claims by visitors who have been injured by a fall in the office do not arise from breach of a professional duty. These claims would be covered by a Public Liability policy.
The policy is a ‘claims made’ policy; in other words it responds only to claims made during the currency of the policy. The negligent act, error or omission giving rise to the claim may have been committed some years previously but the policy nevertheless applies (assuming the negligent act, error or omission was unknown to the insured at the time a proposal was made for insurance — if it was previously known but not disclosed to the insurers, the insurers may avoid the policy because of the non-disclosure of material fact).

Once the policy lapses there is no cover, notwithstanding the fact that a negligent act, error or omission was committed during the currency. The sole test is: was the policy in force at the date of the claim?

Cover relates only to a negligent act, error or omission. The wording is important since if liability arises solely under a warranty, fitness-for-purpose or guarantee clause in the contract for professional services, there may not have been a negligent act, error or omission and there would thus be no cover.
There is a limit of indemnity up to which insurers will pay claims, but not beyond. This limit is usually an aggregate for all claims in any one policy year.
Insurers will pay the costs and expenses incurred with their consent in the defence or settlement of any claim. However, if the claim is ultimately settled at a higher value than the limit of indemnity, the legal costs and expenses are shared in proportion to the claim and the limit of indemnity. Thus if the limit of indemnity is £2 million and the claim is settled for £4 million, the insurers will pay only one-half of the legal costs and expenses.
It is important to insure for an adequate limit. Claims often take a long time to settle and upwards of five years is not unusual. The effects of inflation and monetary values applying at the date of settlement which may increase substantially the cost of a claim must be taken into consideration.
The ‘business’ will be carefully defined in the policy, and the policy will operate only in respect of those business activities defined. Care is therefore necessary to see that the description is sufficiently wide and covers all the professional duties to be performed.
Contractual agreements in connection with consortia and joint ventures are a matter which require particular scrutiny. Insurers should be fully advised of the contractual arrangements and agreement reached as to exactly what cover is necessary in order to obtain full cover of the insured’s risks. A professional firm may find itself carrying the responsibilities of other parties; this can have serious consequences if those other parties are uninsured or go out of business. This should be considered in consultation with the insurers.
An annual policy may exclude work outside the United Kingdom, particularly in the United States and Canada. This is because professional liability exposures in overseas countries may differ substantially from liability exposures in the UK. In addition it will be important to establish which system of law will govern any dispute, i.e. English or foreign law. Even if work abroad is covered, it may be subject to a legal jurisdiction clause in the policy, e.g. that claims are only covered if they are madein UK courts. Such jurisdiction clauses must be read with care and their meaning understood.
It may be difficult, if not impossible, always to obtain adequate cover for injury, damage or loss of use of property arising from seepage, pollution or contamination (including the costs of removing, neutralising and cleaning up afterwards) which have resulted from the consulting engineer’s activities. Typical provisions in the policy schedule stating limits of indemnity now include additionally a limitation that cover for claims in respect of seepage, pollution or contamination shall notexceed an aggregate amount in any one year. The long-term availability of professional indemnity cover remains in doubt at the time of writing.

Extensions to cover

It is usually possible to extend a basic policy to give additional cover for risks such as the following.

Libel or slander.
Third parties who have sustained losses arising out of the fraud or dishonesty of employees. Deliberate acts of fraud or dishonesty by employees are not normally covered by the policy, which refers to any ‘negligent act, error or omission’, i.e. some inadvertent mistake. Thus an employee may deliberately give misleading information, destroy plans, records or documents, give false certificates or permit other acts of dishonesty for which his/her employer may be liable. The extension does not cover loss of the employer’s own money or property, which should be the subject of separate Fidelity Guarantee insurance. The policy is intended to cover claims by third parties, not by the insured.
Infringement of copyright.
Protection to employees in addition to the named Insured. Legally, having settled a claim against the named Insured arising out of an employee’s negligence, the insurers could have rights of subrogation against the employees concerned. An ‘indemnity to employees’ or a ‘waiver of subrogation rights against employees’ clause gives protection to the employee.
Loss of documents. This covers liability for the consequences of loss of documents which have been entrusted to or belong to the insured. Besides legal liability, the extension may include reasonable costs in replacing or restoring documents.

Disclosure of all known material facts

As discussed in Chapter 1, before insurers issue a Professional Indemnity policy, they will require the completion of a proposal form asking a number of specific questions. The answers to the questions must be complete and the Insured must not fail to disclose any material facts that may have a bearing on the underwriter’s acceptance of the risk or terms and conditions agreed.

The duty to disclose all material facts arises again at renewal. It is usual for insurers to ask for the completion of a declaration form (or in some cases a new proposal form) at each renewal date of the policy because at that time a new insurance contract comes into existence.

The person signing the proposal form should consult with all relevant persons to make sure that all material facts are disclosed and the proposal form has been completed correctly. Anything which is relevant to professional liability or may give rise to a claim or has a bearing on the Professional Indemnity policy should be identified and if in doubt discussed with the insurers. Failure to do so may render cover invalid.

Conditions of policy

There are a number of important policy conditions which normally must be complied with. Failure to do so may prejudice a policy and insurers can then refuse to indemnify the Insured. It is important to comply with policy conditions such as the following.

The Insured must not admit liability or in any other way attempt to negotiate or compromise a claim. All negotiations will be carried out by the insurers unless they give permission for the Insured to do so.
To avoid adverse publicity and differences of opinion between the Insured and the insurers, the Insured must not contest any legal proceedings unless advice from a legal representative mutually agreed upon by the Insured and the insurers advises that such proceedings should be contested.
The Insured must give immediate notification to the insurers of any claim made, or receipt of any information from any person of an intention to make a claim, against the Insured. This includes the Insured becoming aware of any occurrence which can subsequently give rise to a claim (even though no claim has been made at the time). For example, an Insured may discover a serious mistake in calculations which has not yet given rise to a claim, or he may have reason to believe a design is faulty. Most policies provide that once that occurrence has been reported to the insurers, any subsequent claim which may be made against the Insured arising out of that occurrence (even if many years later) will be deemed to have been made during the currency of the policy in force when the occurrence was notified.

Typical provisions for Professional Indemnity within Contractor’s design and construct contracts

Clause 8(2) of both of ICE 6 and ICE Design and Construct conditions of contract limits a Contractor’s design obligation to ‘all reasonable skill, care and due diligence’. There is no requirement for a Contractor or a Contractor’s designer (whether in-house or from an outside consultancy) to obtain Professional Indemnity insurance. This is a matter for the Contractor and/or consultant to decide, unless an Employer specifically requires compulsory Professional Indemnity insurance to be held by the Contractor, by so stating in an additional clause to the standard conditions of contract.

A Contractor will be liable when his design faults affect the Works, whether there is negligence or not. A typical Professional Indemnity policy will only normally cover ‘negligent acts errors or omissions’. It will not therefore give a Contractor’s design department protection where there is no negligence.

Typical provisions for Professional Indemnity within Contractor’s other policies

Aspects of Contractor’s professional negligence risk may be covered in different Contractor policies.

Contractor’s Professional Indemnity policy

A specimen Contractor’s Professional Indemnity policy is provided in Appendix 6. The following points are briefly noted.

Third party risks (i.e. loss of or damage to third party property) may or may not be included in a Contractor’s design department’s Professional Indemnity policy. There would, of course, be no need to include them if they are covered by a Public Liability policy.
The Contractor’s Professional Indemnity policy’s main purpose is to provide cover for claims by others for damage to or faults (where those are due to some neglect, error or omission on the part of the Contractor’s design department) in the contract works after practical completion. However, ‘first party’ cover is sometimes included in Contractor’s design and construction Professional Indemnity policies to cover the Contractor’s costs of rectifying faults discovered during the construction period and prior to handover.

Contractor’s Public Liability policy

This policy protects a Contractor against legal liability for injury to third parties and physical damage to property of third parties, plus any third party consequential losses which may flow from that injury or damage. It will usually cover the ‘professional’ activities of a Contractor which might give rise to such damage, provided there is no specific policy exclusion of claims due to breach of professional duty or arising from advice, design, plan or specification.
It does not cover damage to the contract works: that is the purpose of a Contractor’s Contract Works policy.

Contractor’s Contract Works policy

This policy is primarily to cover damage to the contract works during construction. It will normally exclude damage to the works arising out of design, plan or specification. The exclusion may be modified (refer to DE Clauses as described in Chapter 10) so that it is only a defective part which is excluded. Thus, if the defective part causes damage to non-defective parts, damage to those non-defective parts is covered. Problems arise in practice in defining which is the ‘part’ and what constitutes ‘damage’.

Appendix 5. Typical consulting engineer’s Professional Indemnity policy

Comments on the following specimen Professional Indemnity insurance policy are in Chapter 15.

WHEREAS THE Insured named in the Schedule have made a written proposal, bearing the date stated in the Schedule containing particulars and statements which it is hereby agreed are the basis of this Policy and are to be considered as incorporated herein, and have paid the premium stated in the Schedule.

NOW WE, the Insurers, to the extent and in the manner hereinafter provided, hereby agree to indemnify the Insured against any claim for damages for breach of professional duty which may be made against them during the period of insurance due to any negligent act error or omission whenever or wherever the same was or was alleged to have been committed by the Insured or their predecessors in business or any employee of the Insured or their predecessors in business in the conduct of the business.

THE LIABILITY of the Insurers shall not exceed the Limits of Liability stated in the Schedule in respect of each claim, or series of claims, arising out of one source or cause, under this insurance except that the Insurers agree to pay, in addition to the limits of liability, all costs and expenses incurred with their written consent in the investigation, defence or settlement of any claim under this insurance.

IN THE EVENT that any claim exceeeds the indemnity available under this Policy the Insurers hereon shall not be liable for the total costs and expenses in respect of that claim but shall contribute to the total costs and expense in the proportion that the indemnity paid under this Policy in respect of that claim bears to the total indemnity paid by this policy and any Policies effected in excess hereof.

HOWEVER, the Insurers shall only be liable in respect of any claim under this insurance for that part of the claim, or that part of the aggregate of a series of claims arising out of one source of cause, which exceeds the amount stated in the Schedule as the ‘Excess’.

Exceptions

The Insurers shall not be liable in respect of:

1. any loss brought about or contributed to by the dishonesty of any of the Insured’s partners or directors.
2. any claim arising from the loss of money or securities by theft, embezzlement or misappropriation by any of the Insured’s employees.
3. any legal liability of whatsoever nature directly or indirectly caused by or contributed to by or arising from:

(a) ionising radiations or contamination by radioactivity from any nuclear fuel or from any nuclear waste from the combustion of nuclear fuel;
(b) the radioactive toxic explosive or other hazardous properties of any explosive nuclear assembly or nuclear component thereof.

Memoranda

Memo 1. Project managers’ extension

This Insurance is extended to include the Insured’s activities as Project Managers.

Provided always that this extension shall only cover the Insured for their legal liability for negligent acts, errors or omissions as managers of a project where they are remunerated for a fee for their services and shall be limited to the overall control and general supervision of the contract. This extension shall not however cover claims made against the Insured for

(a) any claim resulting from a failure to procure or maintain any financing for the payment of contract work or services in connection therewith from any cause whatsoever.
(b) any claim which would normally be the responsibility of the building contractor if a separate Project Manager were not appointed
(c) any claim as a result of failure to effect and/or maintain insurance
(d) insolvency of any of the parties involved in the project
(e) any liability assumed by the Insured under contract which would not have attached to them but for the existence of the contract
(f) error or omission by the Insured in estimates of probable construction cost or cost estimates being exceeded.

All other terms and conditions remain unaltered.

Memo 2. Libel and slander extension

Subject otherwise to the terms, clauses and conditions of this Policy, the Insurers will indemnify the Insured for all sums which the Insured may become legally liable to pay in respect of claims made upon them in direct consequences of any libel or slander uttered by the Insured in their professional capacity, provided that this insurance shall not extend to any matter contained in a journal or publication or in any communication or contribution to the Press, Radio or Television.

Memo 3. Dishonesty of employees extension

Subject otherwise to the terms, clauses and conditions of this Policy, the Insurers will indemnify the Insured for any claim brought about, or contributed to, by the dishonest, fraudulent, criminal or malicious act or omission of any person at any time employed by the Insured.

Memo 4. Loss of documents extension

Notwithstanding anything contained herein to the contrary, it is understood and agreed that if during the currency of this Policy the Insured shall discover, and shall within seven days of the date of discovery give written notice thereof to the Insurers, that any Documents (as hereinafter defined) the property of, or entrusted to, the Insured which now or hereafter are or are by them supposed to believed to be in their hands or in the hands of any other Party or Parties to or with whom such Documents have been entrusted, lodged or deposited by the Insured in the ordinary course of business have been destroyed or damaged or lost or mislaid and after diligent search cannot be found this Policy shall indemnify the Insured for

(a) any liabilities of whatsoever nature which they may incur to Third Parties in consequence of such Documents having been so destroyed, damaged, lost or mislaid.
(b) all costs, charges and expenses of whatsoever nature incurred by the insured in replacing and/or restoring such Documents.

Provided always that

1. the amount of any claim for costs and expenses as above shall be supported by Bills and/or Accounts which shall be subject to approval by some competent person to be nominated by the Insurers with the approval of the Insured.
2. no liability shall attach hereto for any loss brought about or contributed to by the dishonesty of any of the Insured’s partners.
3. on payment of any loss hereunder, the Insured shall subrogate to insurers their right of procedure against any other person or persons for the recovery thereof.
4. Insurers’ liability in respect of any and all losses hereunder shall be limited to the sum of £10,000.
5. the Excess as stated in the Schedule of the Policy wording shall not apply to this Loss of Documents Extension.
6. ‘Documents’ shall mean Deeds, Wills, Agreements, Maps, Plans, Records, written or printed Books, Letters, Certificates or written or printed Documents and/or Forms of any nature whatsoever (excluding, however, any Bearer Bonds or Coupons, Bank or Currency Notes or other negotiable paper) used in connection with the Insured’s business.
7. It is understood and agreed that the limit of liability under this Loss of Documents Extension is in addition to the limit of liability as stated in the Schedule.
8. For the purposes of this extension and no other the Excess is £50 for each and every claim.

Memo 5

Subject otherwise to the terms, clauses and conditions of this Policy the Insurers will indemnify the past, present or future partners and employees of the Insured as co-assured, provided that such partners and employees shall comply with the terms and conditions of this Policy in so far as they can apply.

Memo 6

The Insurers hereby agree to pay all costs incurred by the Insured in connection with legal proceedings taken by the Insured for the recovery of professional fees due in accordance with the Scale of Professional Charges sanctioned by the Association of Consulting Engineers provided that:

(a) no claim under this Clause shall attach unless and until

(i) the Insured has instituted proceedings for recovery and
(ii) the party sued has intimated his intention to raise by way of answer a counter-claim such as would be covered under this insurance.

(b) the Insurers shall be advised if any intended claim immediately the grounds of the defence have been disclosed to the Insured.

Memo 7

It is noted and agreed that the term ‘employee’ as used in the Policy shall be deemed to include ‘freelance employees’ engaged by the Insured.

Memo 8

It is noted and agreed that this insurance shall indemnify the Insured against liability arising out of work performed by sub-contractors on the Insured’s behalf. However, the insurers shall retain their full rights of subrogation in respect thereof.

Memo 9

It is noted and agreed that subject otherwise to the terms, exclusions, limitations and conditions of the Policy it is hereby understood and agreed that the practice(s) as Consulting Engineers referred to in the Insuring Clause shall be deemed to include the commissioning of installations, including physical work done by the Insured in connection therewith, and the preparation of planned maintenance documentation, manuals and schedules.

Conditions

1. Immediate notice shall be given by the Insured in writing to the Insurers of

(i) any claim or intimation to the Insured of possible claim made against the Insured which may give rise to a claim under this Policy.
(ii) any occurrence or circumstance, of which the Insured shall become aware during the subsistence of this Policy, which may subsequently give rise to a claim against the Insured. Such notice having been given, any claim, to which that occurrence or circumstance has given rise, which may be made after the expiration of the period specified in the Schedule shall be deemed to be made during the subsistence of this Policy for the purposes of this insurance.

Furthermore the Insured shall upon request give to the Insurers all such information and assistance as the Insurers may reasonably require and as may be in the Insured’s power and will in all such matters do and concur in doing all such things as the Insurers may require.

2. The Insured shall not be required to contest any legal proceedings unless a Queen’s Counsel (to be mutually agreed upon) shall advise that such claim could be contested with a reasonable prospect of success and the Insured consents thereto such consent not to be unreasonably withheld. In the event of a difference of opinion between the Insured and the Insurers as to what constitutes an unreasonable refusal the Chairman for the time being of the Association of Consulting Engineers shall nominate an independent referee to decide this point only and the decision of such referee shall be binding on the Insured and the Insurers.
3. All differences arising out of this Policy shall be referred to the arbitration of some person to be appointed by both parties or if they cannot agree upon a single arbitrator to the decision of two arbitrators one to be appointed in writing by each party and in case of disagreement between the arbitrators to the decision of an umpire who shall have been appointed in writing by the arbitrators before entering on the reference and an award shall be a condition precedent to any liability of the Insurers or any right of action against the Insurers. The provisions of the Arbitration Acts shall apply to any such arbitration and the place of arbitration shall be London England.
4. If the Insurers shall disclaim liability to the Insured in respect of any claim made upon the Insured the Insured shall be at liberty without prejudice to his claim for indemnity hereunder to settle or compromise such claims or submit to any judgement or arbitration award in respect thereof and the sum payable by the Insured in respect of any such settlement compromise judgement or arbitration award in respect thereof and the sum payable by the Insured in respect of any such settlement compromise judgement or arbitration award shall be accepted by the Insurers as the amount payable by the Insurers to the Insured subject to the terms of this Policy and subject to the liability of the Insurers being established by arbitration as herein provided.
5. The due observance and fulfilment of the terms and conditions of this policy so far as they relate to anything to be done or complied with by the Insured and the truth of any proposal shall be conditions precedent to any liability of the Insurers to make any payment under this Policy.
6. If any payment is made under this insurance in respect of a claim the Insurers are thereupon subrogated to all the Insured’s rights of recovery in relation thereto. However, the Insurers shall not exercise any rights against any employee of the Insured unless the claim has been brought about or contributed to by the dishonest, fraudulent, criminal or malicious act or omission of the employee.
7. If at the time any claim arises under this Insurance the Insured is or would but for the existence of this Insurance be entitled to indemnity under any other policy or policies the Insurers shall not be liable except in respect of any excess beyond the amount which would have been payable under such other policy or policies had this Insurance not been effected.
8.If the Insured shall make any claim knowing the same to be false or fraudulent as regards amount or otherwise this Insurance shall become void and all claim hereunder shall be forfeited.

1. THE INSURED:
2. ADDRESS OF THE INSURED:
3. THE PERIOD OF INSURANCE:
4. THE INDEMNITY:
5. THE EXCESS:
6. THE PREMIUM:
7. DATE OF PROPOSAL FORM:
8. TERRITORIAL LIMITS:
9. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES AND DUTIES:

Appendix 6. Typical Contractor’s Professional Indemnity policy

Comments on the following specimen professional indemnity insurance policy are made very briefly in Chapter 15.

WHEREAS the Insured has made a written proposal to Us, the Underwriters, which proposal together with other information supplied by the Insured, shall be deemed to be incorporated herein and shall be the basis of this contract and has paid to us the premium stated in the Schedule.

NOW THEREFORE, We, the Underwriters jointly agree to indemnify the Insured up to but not exceeding the indemnity stated in the Schedule for any sum or sums which the Insured may become legally liable to pay arising from any claim or claims made against them during the period stated in the Schedule as a result of any negligent act, error and/or omission in the conduct and execution of all their professional activities and duties.

Provided always that the Underwriters’ liability in respect of all claims shall not exceed the indemnity stated in the Schedule.

FURTHER, it is understood and agreed that the Underwriters will pay in addition to the indemnity stated in the Schedule costs and expenses incurred with the Underwriters’ written consent in the defence and/or settlement of any claim. However, if a payment in excess of the amount of indemnity available under this insurance has to be made to dispose of a claim, the Underwriters’ liability in respect of such costs and expenses incurred shall be such as the amount of the indemnity available under this insurance bears to the total amount paid to dispose of the claim.

The excess

PROVIDED ALWAYS THAT THE Underwriters shall be liable only, in respect of any one claim, for that part of the claim which exceeds the relevant excess stated in the Schedule. It being understood and agreed that if any expenditure is incurred by the Underwriters which, by virtue of this clause, is the responsibility of the Insured then such amount shall be reimbursed to the Underwriters by the Insured forthwith on demand.

Exclusions

This Policy does not cover any claims or claims arising out of:

(i) Bodily injury sustained by any person arising out of and in the course of his employment by the Insured under a contract of service or apprenticeship with the Insured.
(ii) Any neglect, error and/or omission to effect or maintain insurance and/or to provide finance or advice on financial matters.
(iii) Any claim against the Insured for libel and/or slander and/or as a result of any dishonest, malicious, criminal or illegal acts of the Insured.
(iv) The insolvency of the Insured.
(v) The ownership, use and/or occupation of property mobile and/ or immobile including waterborne vessels or craft or aircraft or motor vehicles by, to or on behalf of the Insured.
(vi) The cost of replacing documents which have been lost, mislaid or destroyed.
(vii) Any legal liability of whatsoever nature directly or indirectly caused by or contributed to by or arising from

(a) ionising radiations or contamination by radioactivity from any nuclear fuel or from any waste from the combustion of nuclear fuel.
(b) the radioactive, toxic, explosive or other hazardous properties of any exposive nuclear assembly or nuclear component thereof.

This Policy shall not indemnify the Insured against liability for any fines, penalties, punitive or exemplary damages and/or liquidated damages.

Special provisions

Where the Insured incur loss or expenses in remedying defects in any contract works and arising from any negligent act, error and/or omission in connection with their professional activities and duties, the Underwriters agree to consider such loss or expense as a claim against the Insured.

Provided always that

(a) such defect is discovered prior to handover of such contract works to the Insured’s employer,
(b) the burden of proving any claim under this Special Provision shall be upon the Insured,
(c) there shall be excluded from any indemnity under this Special Provision any amount recoverable or which would be recoverable but for this exclusion under any other insurance policy.

Conditions

Insured’s duties in the event of a claim

(i) The Insured shall as a condition precedent to their right to be indemnified under this insurance give immediate written notice to the person(s) named for that purpose in the Schedule for transmission to the Underwriters

(a) of any claim made against them,
(b) of the receipt of notice from any person of an intention to make a claim against them,
(c) of any defect in any contract works following which loss or expense may be incurred by the Insured in accordance with Special Provision 1 (One),
(d) of any circumstance of which they shall become aware during the period stated in the Schedule, which is likely to give rise to a claim against them. Such notice having been given, any claim, to which that circumstance has given rise, which may be made after the expiration of the period stated in the Schedule shall be deemed for the purpose of this Policy to have been made during the period stated in the Schedule.

(ii) The Insured shall not admit liability or settle or make or promise any payment in respect of any claim which may be the subject of indemnity hereunder or incur any costs or expenses in connection therewith without the written consent of the Underwriters who if they so wish shall be entitled to take over and conduct in the name of the Insured the defence and/or settlement of any such claim for which purpose the Insured shall give all such information and assistance as the Underwriters may reasonably require.

Litigation

The Underwriters will not require the Insured to dispute any claim unless a Queen’s Counsel or lawyer of comparable standing in the territory concerned (to be mutually agreed upon by the Underwriters and the Insured) advise that the same could be contested with a reasonable prospect of success by the Insured and the Insured consents to such claim being contested, such consent not to be unreasonably withheld. In the event of any dispute arising between the Insured and the Underwriters as to what constitutes an unreasonable refusal to contest a claim at law, the President for the time being of the Chartered Institute of Arbitrators shall nominate a Referee to decide this point (only) and the decision of such Referee shall be binding on both parties.

Subrogation

It is hereby agreed that if any payment is made under this insurance in respect of a claim the Underwriters are thereupon subrogated to all the Insured’s rights of recovery in relation thereto. However, the Underwriters shall not exercise any such rights against any employee of the Insured unless the claim has been bought about or contributed to by the dishonest, fraudulent, criminal or malicious act or omission of the employee.

Fraudulent claims

If an Insured shall make any claim knowing the same to be fraudulent or false, as regards amount or otherwise, this insurance shall become void and all claims hereunder shall be forfeited in respect of that particular Insured.

Other insurance

Insofar as it is within their power the Insured will produce information regarding any other insurance of the Insured’s professional activities and duties on receipt of the Underwriters’ request.

Non-contribution clause

If the liability which is the subject of a claim under this Policy is covered by any other insurance and that insurance has a NonContribution Clause, the Underwriters under this Policy will not pay more than their rateable proportion.

It is understood and agreed that this Clause does not apply to claims the subject matter of Memo 3 or Special Provision 1 (One).

Dishonesty of employees

It is understood and agreed, subject otherwise to the terms, exclusions, limitations and conditions contained in this Policy, that this Policy is extended to indemnify the Insured for any claim brought about, or contributed to, by the dishonest, fraudulent, criminal or malicious act or omission of any person at any time employed by the Insured.

Infringement of copyright

It is understood and agreed, subject otherwise to the terms, exclusions, limitations and conditions contained in this Policy, that this Policy is extended to indemnify the Insured for any claim or claims made against the Insured arising out of any infringement of copyright or breach of patent.

THE INSURED:
ADDRESS OF THE INSURED:
THE PERIOD OF INSURANCE:
THE INDEMNITY:
THE EXCESS:
THE PREMIUM:
DATE OF PROPOSAL FORM:
TERRITORIAL LIMITS: Worldwide
PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES AND DUTIES

Work undertaken by the Design Department
Feasibility Studies

Bibliography

The following list is not intended to be comprehensive, but is suggested as a basis for further reading on the topics contained in the text.

Cottam G. and Hawker G. ICE Conditions for Minor Works: a user’s guide and commentary. Thomas Telford, London, 1992.

Eaglestone F.N. and Smyth C. Insurance under the ICE Contract. George Godwin, London, 1985.

Eaglestone F.N. Contractors’ all risks insurance. Chartered Institute of Loss Adjusters, London, 1993.

Edwards Leslie, Practical risk management in the construction industry.

Thomas Telford, London, 1995.

Eggleston B. ICE Design and Construct Contract. 1994.

Eggleston B. ICE Conditions of Contract: 6th edition. 1993.

Hickson R.J. Construction insurance: management and claims. E&FN Spon, London, 1987.

Institution of Civil Engineers. ICE Conditions of Contract 6th Edition — guidance notes. ICE, ACE, FCEC, London, 1991.

Institution of Civil Engineers. ICE Design and Construct Conditionsof Contract — guidance notes. ICE, ACE, FCEC, London, 1991.

Insurance Institute of London. Construction and erection insurance Advanced Study Group 2O8B). London, Draft 1996.

Levine Marshall and Wood Jeremy. Construction insurance and UK construction contracts. Lloyds of London Press, London, 1991.

Wright John D. Construction insurance CII Coursebook 650. Witherby, 1991.